<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fair character of the Presbyterian reformling's just and sober vindication of his observations upon the 30th of January, and the 29th of May, in defence of the reformer rack'd. Being an answer to J.G.G.'s new vile rant, and the Weekly Observator's invidious and false reflections on it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F94A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012435</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012435</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174404</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174404)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2687:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fair character of the Presbyterian reformling's just and sober vindication of his observations upon the 30th of January, and the 29th of May, in defence of the reformer rack'd. Being an answer to J.G.G.'s new vile rant, and the Weekly Observator's invidious and false reflections on it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On t.p.: "Fiat justitia, ruat novus reformator."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gailhard, J. --  (Jean).</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174404:1"/>
            <p>A Fair CHARACTER OF THE Presbyterian Reformling's <hi>Juſt and Sober</hi> VINDICATION OF HIS OBSERVATIONS <hi>Upon the</hi> 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> January, <hi>and</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> May, In Defence of the <hi>REFORMER RACK'D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING An ANSWER to <hi>J.G.G.</hi>'s New vile RANT, and the <hi>Weekly Obſervator</hi>'s invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and falſe Reflections on it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiat Juſtitia, ruat novus Reformator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed in the Year 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:174404:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174404:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THis Prefatory Occaſion to the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Character <hi>of the</hi> Presbyterian Reformer, <hi>is taken from the</hi> Weekly Obſervator<hi>'s Reflections on</hi> two Pamphlets: Obſervations <hi>upon,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and my</hi> Remarks <hi>upon them. Obſerv. Vol.</hi> 7. <hi>Numb.</hi> 24. <hi>Saturday June</hi> 30. 1694. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Inteſtine Diviſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For an</hi> Author <hi>to appear in</hi> Print <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a</hi> Preface, <hi>by ſome</hi> fopling Criticks <hi>is reckoned as ungenteel and</hi> wild, <hi>as for</hi> Ray <hi>the Madman to</hi> haire <hi>it about</hi> Town <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his</hi> Cravat <hi>on, or the</hi> Court-Baux <hi>to air in the</hi> Park <hi>without a</hi> Steinkirk Twiſted-poſt Neckcloth: <hi>Juſt ſo perhaps for the</hi> Compleat Attorney <hi>not to</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble
<pb facs="tcp:174404:3"/>
               <hi>in his Dreſſing-room to his Glaſs or</hi> falſe Reflector <hi>before he flings into</hi> Grays-Inn Walks <hi>or expatiates into the Fields, is inconſiderate and</hi> Sloven-like. <hi>I am now in the</hi> Faſhion; <hi>thank</hi> Mr. Obſervator: <hi>but if we would ſubmit, and</hi> Valet <hi>it to his</hi> Latitudinarian Nicety <hi>and</hi> Modiſh Looſeneſs, <hi>ſhould we not</hi> Preface <hi>our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation of the</hi> Church of England's Upbraidings <hi>and Inveighings againſt the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>with a</hi> peccavimus omnes <hi>in our Mouths, or a confeſſory or</hi> revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Rope <hi>about our</hi> Necks? <hi>God-a-mercy</hi> Mercurius Brittanicus <hi>for this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>J.G.G. <hi>has Vindicated his</hi> Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>and I have here a</hi> Counter-Cuffe <hi>for the</hi> Vindicator <hi>as well as the</hi> Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator; <hi>but it is</hi> Two <hi>to</hi> One <hi>that the</hi> Caſtle in the Air <hi>goes down, and I am</hi> worſted <hi>in the Engagement. Mighty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts indeed,</hi> Pelion upon Oſſa-Blades! <hi>And when I come on my</hi> Marrow-Bones <hi>to either for</hi> Quarter,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Farewel</hi> Reader.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174404:3"/>
            <head>A Fair Character of the Presbyterian Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling's, <hi>Juſt and Sober Vindication of his Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon the Thirtieth of</hi> January <hi>and Twenty ninth of</hi> May, — <hi>in Defence of the</hi> Reformer Rack'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Reformling would gladly be reputed Juſt and Sober in his Vindication, and if the World will take it upon the <hi>credit</hi> of his Title Page, or read no more of his Vertues, than what they may do <hi>Walking,</hi> upon a <hi>placarted great Gate,</hi> or a <hi>plaſtered Sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt,</hi> he may be ſo ſtill in a vulgar <hi>Eye.</hi> Sober! what? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he has ſo <hi>out-run</hi> the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> But, <hi>ſtand</hi> in the Name of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> can he be Juſt too that does ſo? Well, however he ſets a good <hi>Face</hi> on the matter, and carries himſelf Juſt and Sober in his <hi>Frontiſpiece,</hi> and as ſure as <hi>Caudles</hi> are <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> he that will <hi>herd</hi> among the Sober Party, muſt look as modeſt and demure, as a Whore at a <hi>Chriſtening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many a good old <hi>Sign</hi> promiſes <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Mortification</hi> enough, when there is nothing but revelling, rant, <hi>Hey-go-mad,</hi> Murder—Watch! Watch! within: Some Men will not keep the peace, becauſe it is the Kings, nor keep the Kings nor keep the Church, becauſe it is not Theirs, and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> or <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> never eſtabliſhed nor <hi>endowed</hi> it. But up <hi>ſtalk Mid-night-juſtice,</hi> and the Raunters no ſooner ſee the <hi>Staff</hi> and the <hi>Lanthorn</hi> appear, but they are as Juſt and Sober as <hi>Peace</hi> can make them; every Man is ready with his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication in his Mouth, and nothing falls out but <hi>good Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood</hi> between the <hi>Cup and the Lip.</hi> This might <hi>ſuit</hi> J.G.G. for a <hi>Tiring-Room,</hi> where to put on his Vizards of <hi>Truth, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> and <hi>Soberneſs;</hi> and be a proper <hi>Stage</hi> for the <hi>Impoſtor</hi> to <hi>maſque</hi> the face of a <hi>lye</hi> or reproach, and to act his <hi>falſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> on. Here's likewiſe the exact Emblem of our Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſmoothing o're, and <hi>palliating</hi> a quarrelſome buſineſs; a <hi>ſerene</hi> brow with a <hi>Head-ful</hi> of <hi>Storms,</hi> and the <hi>Aeolus</hi> ſpeaks
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174404:4"/>fair, breaths a ſoft and gentle <hi>breeze,</hi> when he deſigns a <hi>Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane</hi> the next blaſt. His <hi>Title</hi> forſooth, muſt needs be a Juſt and Sober <hi>Vindicator;</hi> but to <hi>Vindicate</hi> the Truth of that, and juſtifie the <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> he might ſwell his <hi>Fuſtian</hi> into a bigger Volume of Faction, and never make a better Cloak on't, nor the true <hi>Herald</hi> ever think him worthier of a <hi>Coat of Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's a Comical Story of one <hi>Aletheia Gray</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> Chriſtened with <hi>Truth</hi> enough: Her <hi>Name</hi> had ſome <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> in it, tho' her <hi>Nature</hi> had none; for ſhe prov'd as great a lyer as any of the <hi>Maſculine Sex</hi> in the Kingdom, and ſo noted, it's believed that ſhe might have carryed off the <hi>Whet-ſtone</hi> at <hi>Temple-Sowerby</hi> in ſpite of her <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> This may be a pretty Siſter-Motto for <hi>J.G.G's juſt falſeneſs</hi> and revengefulneſs, and <hi>Aletheia Lyar</hi> might very well have weigh'd the <hi>Panniers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſober <hi>Madneſs</hi> in his <hi>Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sober Gentleman!</hi> Ah! What ſhould <hi>ale</hi> him unleſs <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> intoxicate, for a Man ſometimes grows <hi>drunk</hi> with his <hi>Cordial. Juſt</hi> too! no doubt of it; if he have <hi>Authority,</hi> he'll act within his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> although his <hi>ſtomaching</hi> pride knows no rules of <hi>devouring;</hi> He is a fooliſh <hi>Cobler</hi> that goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his <hi>Laſt.</hi> But it's an unfortunate thing to be <hi>confined</hi> or <hi>encircled,</hi> except it be to keep the Devil out: His <hi>Sphere</hi> is not large enough for all <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and an honeſter Man may grow <hi>giddy</hi> with the <hi>rapt</hi> and <hi>motion</hi> of his own nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Orb</hi> with <hi>Toleration.</hi> Thus like a <hi>turn-ſick</hi> Child at run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>round-play,</hi> the civil <hi>Copernican</hi> may chance to reel, and make a falſe <hi>ſtep</hi> of Ambition over the Globe, to juſtle out his Neighbouring <hi>lights</hi> and keep himſelf ſtill in the <hi>dark,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving all the while his farther diſtance from the <hi>Sun; The Son of Righteouſneſs and Peace.</hi> He may indeed bid as <hi>fair</hi> for Heaven, by his gloryed <hi>Juſtneſs</hi> and <hi>Seberneſs,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> as another for any thing I ſhall tell him yet of <hi>treading his own An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes,</hi> to a Heavenly <hi>Union;</hi> let him make his way thither as faſt as he can: But in the interim, let him be adviſed to be <hi>content</hi> with his own <hi>ſtation</hi> and <hi>lot</hi> here; <hi>be wiſe on this ſide Heaven,</hi> not mutinous on this ſide of the <hi>Water,</hi> and then I wiſh him his <hi>Belly full</hi> of <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>Honey</hi> beyond it. In ſine therefore of his factious Covetouſneſs, when his <hi>adulterate Aſtraea</hi> has pimped <hi>Victoria</hi> to his inſatiable embraces, and he becomes <hi>maſter</hi> of one World, let not the imperious ſpirit of our <hi>Alexander</hi> make him weep and put his <hi>Finger</hi> in his <hi>greedy Eye</hi> for <hi>another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174404:4"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding a <hi>Brother full of the Creature</hi> may be <hi>Sober</hi> and <hi>Juſt</hi> too; the <hi>Club</hi> of Saints have perhaps a <hi>Sober Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham-Barn Statute,</hi> to make their own <hi>Indentures as they go,</hi> and <hi>Stagger</hi> all the <hi>Laws</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to keep their own <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiant Legiſlations</hi> out of the <hi>Kennel.</hi> Such a <hi>Brother</hi> I have ſeen lately <hi>Stamping</hi> it homewards, and <hi>moving, paſſing Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine contra dicente,</hi> and, as it were, <hi>Engroſſing</hi> ſome new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of Church-Government with his <hi>Toes,</hi> by the ſame token that a <hi>Bantering wagg</hi> ſaid, he wondered whether his <hi>Socks were Paper, and his Shoes Parchment.</hi> Excuſe; The <hi>Parrot</hi> had got into ill Company. 'Tis excuſable in one of the <hi>Holy Cloak'd Fraternity,</hi> and He's <hi>ſober</hi> enough to be of the Party ſtill. Much <hi>Truth</hi> is in the <hi>Bottle;</hi> but no more of your <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in your <hi>Cups,</hi> pray.</p>
            <p>Ours is a <hi>Soberer Gentleman,</hi> and is <hi>full</hi> of the <hi>Scripture:</hi> He ſeems ſuch a ſworn Enemy to the WHORE, that I believe he would not <hi>Cuckold the</hi> POPE for his <hi>Infallibility. Infal. lible!</hi> no, he had rather be a miſtaken St. <hi>John,</hi> and have no more Religion than is in the 43. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the GOSPEL.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Title page. Page</hi> 3.</note> Whether he or the Printer was better read in the <hi>Geneva,</hi> I determine not in this <hi>Error;</hi> But <hi>EZEKIEL</hi> was like to have loſt a <hi>Text</hi> between them. If this <hi>Scripture</hi> had only been <hi>miſquoted</hi> to an Auditory of <hi>Dear Brethren and Siſters,</hi> there would have been ſpitting on Thumbs, and ruffling of <hi>Dutch</hi> Bibles, to find out <hi>John</hi> 43.9. but then the miſtake might have been huſh'd up and mutter'd for an inſpired piece of his own <hi>Illumination,</hi> or paſſed for the Word of God with the <hi>Godly,</hi> and he not thought a whit the leſs a <hi>Goſpeller or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Prophet,</hi> for the <hi>miſcall.</hi> The 43. of <hi>Go-look,</hi> would have done as well among the <hi>Religious,</hi> I would ſay <hi>Infallible Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſes, ('tis all one in the Greek, as the</hi> Town-talk <hi>has it for</hi> ſameneſs) though they had conſulted St. <hi>Luke</hi> for the <hi>Divinity.</hi> The <hi>Words</hi> then, the words, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are written. — <hi>Now let them put away their Whoredom, and the Carcaſſes of their Kings, far from me, and I will dwell in the midſt of them.</hi> How <hi>Apocriphal,</hi> how uncanonical he renders this <hi>Scripture</hi> in his uſe and application of it! and would make the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeak from his mouth, call the <hi>Dead Kings</hi> WHOREMASTERS in their Graves, and lay all the abominations of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> upon their <hi>Monuments.</hi> As for <hi>King Charles the Firſt's Carcaſs,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:174404:5"/>much good may the <hi>put away</hi> or removal do him; he has his wiſh on't already, if the moſt received and common Fame lies not; and had he Interpreted <hi>This</hi> of <hi>Windſor-Caſtle,</hi> the Prophecy had been fulfilled long ago to his purpoſe: But then he might as well have talked of <hi>Chriſtmas-fare, after Twelfth-day;</hi> yet who will not <hi>remember his Box for all that.</hi> That the <hi>Royal Body</hi> was removed, ſeems to be no <hi>News,</hi> and what became of it a <hi>Courante</hi> need not poſt from the other World to inform us 'Tis believed, if the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> would be ſo Ingenuous, they might ſhorten the <hi>Stage,</hi> and ſave the <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Travail</hi> of a <hi>long tedious Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not bring a railing accuſation againſt any of them; But the <hi>Arch-Angel</hi> contended for the Body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and defied the <hi>Devil,</hi> Jude <hi>Ep. verſe</hi> 9. Let the report, true or falſe, hurt or diſgrace no Body more then it does <hi>him;</hi> for the moſt diſhonourable Interment of <hi>him,</hi> either in a <hi>Vault</hi> or <hi>Ditch,</hi> only gives Foil and Luſtre to Maſſacred CHARLES; and if no miſreport, why ſhould we ſtrive with the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> for <hi>Him,</hi> when Heaven has <hi>Him</hi> no doubt before the <hi>ſtruggle;</hi> and will give <hi>Him</hi> a nobler <hi>Reſurrection</hi> than they did that ſtole <hi>Him</hi> away?
<note place="margin">He has been worſe uſed, if this ſtory be untrue.</note> But let <hi>Englands Iliads</hi> record the ſtory of <hi>Homer</hi>'s, that it was the Honour of Dead <hi>Patroclus,</hi> that two Armies fought for his <hi>Corps.</hi> The <hi>Living</hi> are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not unreaſonably <hi>alarumed</hi> for the Glory of the <hi>Dead.</hi> A <hi>Soveraign</hi> ſo unhumanly perſecuted after Death, deſerves a Monument at leaſt, and <hi>Montroſſes Epitaph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As great an <hi>Additioner</hi> as the <hi>Reformling</hi> would falſly State me to our CHURCH,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fage</hi> 12, 13.</note> I need add little more to thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> I publiſhed before, to clear <hi>the Glorious Kings</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got</hi>'s Defamation and <hi>Perſonal</hi> Aſperſions, but St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s words, <hi>Ep. ad Gelant. Adverſus Obtrectatorum libidinem pugnat meritorum magnitudo.</hi> They have deſerved better rank in the Eſtimations of all Loyal Chriſtians and Subjects: For if <hi>Subjection</hi> were fairly, or even <hi>Parliamentary</hi> now canvaſſed, I doubt whether the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> would in courteſie <hi>d' An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleterre,</hi> or could by their dangerous Principles, be found to be any to <hi>Engliſh Monarchy;</hi> and our <hi>Reformling</hi> may chew the <hi>Cud</hi> twice upon this before he <hi>digeſts</hi> an Eccleſiaſtical or Civil Obedience, to either Church or State. He may be the <hi>Lurdans Fellow-Labourer,</hi> that was troubled with an <hi>Atrophy</hi> of both, <hi>conſume em both,</hi> ſays he, for want of being nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174404:5"/>
               <hi>that is, glutted,</hi> by <hi>either;</hi> and indeed our <hi>Juſt, Sober Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> talks as if he wanted <hi>Preferment</hi> too, by his envying me mine, when he does not know but I may be in <hi>Lobs-pound</hi> to morrow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One King</hi> was laid out in his <hi>Gore</hi> with a murdering <hi>concla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum eſt</hi> in deriſion, and for a <hi>raree ſhow</hi> to the pitying Loyaliſt and dejected <hi>Cavilier:</hi> A jolly Fellow indeed <hi>Catachreſtically</hi> bleſt himſelf at the <hi>ſight,</hi> and was asked, why? ſays he, I am a <hi>Rope-maker.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi>'s heels were trod upon by the ſame Power, and the like Plot; How far from having his Throat cut, or the <hi>Back-ſtroke</hi> and <hi>Fore-ſtroke</hi> of injuſtice, the <hi>Goward</hi> in Eighty one at <hi>Oxford</hi> can tell: Where ſuch as he impudently avouched, — <hi>They wanted a King, whom they might truſt.</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>Non perſuadebis etiamſi perſuaſeris;</hi> A ſenſe of that error will never exſtimulate them to their <hi>Duty;</hi> A <hi>Word</hi> and a <hi>Blow</hi> with the <hi>Ring</hi> is an Old <hi>Parliament-Law,</hi> and happy were the Man that could wreſt the ſame <hi>Club</hi> out of <hi>Hercules</hi>'s Hand; the <hi>Reforming Siſyphus,</hi> will ſtill be row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up the ſame <hi>Stone</hi> he muſt expect to <hi>tumble down</hi> with.</p>
            <p>I would call <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> the two <hi>Poles</hi> of ſteering any Government by, but a <hi>caſt-away,</hi> if it were not for the <hi>artick</hi> and <hi>antartick Oppoſition</hi> that is made of them. But this can break no <hi>ſquares</hi> in a <hi>ſimilitude;</hi> and <hi>Tantive-College</hi> run the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Tribe of <hi>Tantivee-College</hi> run to our Eſtabliſhed <hi>Religion?</hi> A <hi>Scholar</hi> may ſpeak now I hope, and like a <hi>Gentleman.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 2.</note> — <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Did they not uſe all the Spades and Mattocks of Seditious contrivances, to undermine the Foundation of our well eſtabliſht Church-Government? Did they not envy us the ſupport of our Chief Pillars, the Biſhops, whom they would firſt have made weaker, and then pulled down? would they not have let in many Beaſts of the Forreſt to our Vine-yard, by making a breach in our Fence, in taking out three ſtakes from our Hedge of the</hi> 39. <hi>Articles?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Page</hi> 60, 61.</note> Would not they have given encouragement to Diviſions, by granting liberty to Diſſent, and by removing of Penalties, have invited many to tranſgreſs? Did not they take up at the ſecond hand, many Old Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices of innovating a Change; as crying out againſt the unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of</hi> Pluralities, <hi>the inconveniencies of</hi> Non-reſidence, <hi>and affirming the neceſſity of a Redreſs of both? And finally, did they not uſe all methods of irritating the Vulgar to vilifie the Clergy,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174404:6"/>becauſe they were the chief oppoſers of Sedition and perſwaders to Allegiance and Uniformity.</hi> And then in oppoſition to Loyalty; <hi>How Arbitrary and Magiſterial were their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, while they pretended to be doing nothing elſe but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the Arbitrary Power of another? How many Honeſt and Loyal Gentlemen did they force to do the Penance of falling down and Worſhipping them, for ſpeaking. Blaſphemy againſt their Authority, while Treaſon againſt a higher Power paſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned? How croſly and reſolutely did they always deny His Majeſties juſt Demands, though they were to be employed for the Nations ſecurity? And at laſt, how ſaucily would they have cried down the King by debarring him of the priviledge of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Subject, making it unlawful for any one to turn his Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, though on never ſo good ſecurity?</hi>
               </q> This is not the <hi>moity</hi> of what might be ſaid, but perhaps in this caſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The <hi>Vetus Fabula</hi> only wanted the <hi>Curtains drawing</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Candles lighting,</hi> of being acted on an <hi>Oxford Theatre;</hi> and the <hi>Novi Hiſtoriones,</hi> with ſome of the <hi>Veteres</hi> too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, had played their <hi>Parts</hi> of the like <hi>Tragedy</hi> over again; if they had been ſo ſucceſsful, as not to have been hiſſed off before they came to <hi>Prologue to't.</hi> However the <hi>Reformling</hi> will have <hi>King Charles the Second</hi> to be beholden to his <hi>Party</hi> for his Reſtoration, and peaceable injoyment of his Royalty; and certainly he was, juſt as the <hi>Father Dotard</hi> was beholden to the <hi>Son,</hi> who flatter'd him into a <hi>Settlement,</hi> and then burn'd his Houſe about his Ears, for his <hi>Daddy</hi> to roſt his Eggs with. Our <hi>Sons of Faction</hi> could love <hi>uproars</hi> and <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires</hi> too, but that they hate <hi>Rumps,</hi> and it looks too much like <hi>Sacrificing to the Genius</hi> of Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>At an Election of a Member for the approaching Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Oxon,</hi> (The Loyal <hi>Pudſey</hi> and <hi>Whorewood</hi> Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates) it is pleaſantly ſtoried of a brisk Mechanick, in the Van of a Tumultuous <hi>Crowd,</hi> who hearing a <hi>Graduate</hi> exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming no <hi>Round-head,</hi> no <hi>Round-head,</hi> reparteed him with no <hi>Square-head,</hi> no <hi>Square-head;</hi> when all the Univerſity knew they were for no <hi>Head</hi> at all, or at beſt not for a Crown'd <hi>Rowly-Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am afraid I ſhall be tedious on the <hi>face</hi> and <hi>complexion</hi> of his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> but if <hi>length</hi> be not the <hi>Picture</hi> of him, it is his beſt <hi>Character</hi> at a <hi>Vindication,</hi> or one of his <hi>Sixteenthly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loveds.</hi> Now I cannot imagine what he would be at, have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174404:6"/>done or prevented, the <hi>Pope</hi> is not like to be <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> next Year, nor King <hi>JAMES</hi> to be in his <hi>Throne</hi> again the next <hi>Moon. Popery</hi> is out of Doors, he needs but give it an Alms, or ſend the <hi>Cripple</hi> to the next <hi>Conſtable; Authority</hi> will take care of it: But it may be he has an extraordinary knack at <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> he may have as good and Religious a <hi>God-piece</hi> as <hi>King Henry the Eighth,</hi> and can <hi>Whiſtle</hi> a better <hi>Tune</hi> too in Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that would make the <hi>Rabble</hi> Dance a <hi>Common-wealth Moriſco.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reformer</hi> needs but lead up the <hi>Figure of three, four, Heptarchy or a hundred,</hi> the <hi>Piper's</hi> paid: Cut the firſt <hi>Caper,</hi> and proteſt he wiſhes <hi>England</hi> as well as the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> once did <hi>France,</hi> when he ſwore, <hi>He lov'd</hi> France <hi>ſo well, that for one King, he wiſh'd ſhe had twenty,</hi> and then <hi>you are all of a Litter quoth</hi> Lambert. Let me tell you <hi>Lylly</hi>'s <hi>Grammer</hi> comprehended a great deal of policy in it's <hi>Neutram modo, mas modo vulgus,</hi> but it is <hi>Aes in preſenti</hi> that muſt carry on the buſineſs effectually, to perſection, and what not. The <hi>Mobb</hi> love variety, and every Body knows what is as good for a <hi>Sow</hi> as a <hi>Pancake,</hi> — A <hi>Fartical Raskal</hi> that bid a KING kiſs his <hi>Poſteriors,</hi> I conceive and preſume, <hi>ſaving</hi> J.G. G's <hi>preſence,</hi> would make an excellent Tool for his <hi>Arſie-Farſie Reformation.</hi> At this rate every <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> or <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> with a fair Wind and auſpicious opportunity will be invading and <hi>matching Politicks</hi> with <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council;</hi> and if the <hi>Green-pated Reformer</hi> Heads but well, and puts Liberty, and Property, and the Old <hi>State Quibble</hi> of <hi>Perſonal</hi> and <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Capacity,</hi> into the Mouth of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> the Man STUART may be cut off, and the <hi>King</hi> ne're the worſe hurt. A <hi>Second Oliver</hi> may chance to drop out of the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and then defiance to the Powers of the Earth, our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the People</hi> are, as aſſuredly as the <hi>Rebels</hi> againſt <hi>King John</hi> the <hi>Army of God.</hi> Any <hi>New Coin</hi> gains accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the <hi>Lower Mobb</hi> from its Stamp of <hi>Novelty;</hi> and if the <hi>upper ſort of Mobb mints</hi> it but with a popular App<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe, Vogue, and Reputation, it has Credit, Juſtice and Authority enough to abide their <hi>Teſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing our good <hi>Gentleman</hi> does, is as <hi>wiſe</hi> as he can make <hi>Solomon,</hi> not <hi>Solomon</hi> him, to call his Adverſary a <hi>Fool,</hi> and the worſt of the ſort, a ſelf-conceited <hi>Fool:</hi> Surely if <hi>Robin Wiſdom</hi> ſets not up for an <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Fools</hi> not the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174404:7"/>reſt of Mankind, the <hi>Preſs</hi> cannot blame him for it. But the <hi>would-be Solomon,</hi> preſently <hi>ſtarts</hi> a <hi>Fool</hi> out of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> before he enters the <hi>Field;</hi> no, if he had not been beſides the <hi>Buſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 18.</note> and had had the good luck to have thrown his UTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAM SAPEREM ſoon enough in his tail (as the <hi>No vice-hunter</hi> carries <hi>Salt</hi> to catch the <hi>Hare</hi> with) he had taken him too, and might have <hi>Sounded</hi> his Triumph of the <hi>Prey</hi> at the firſt <hi>View.</hi> Many a one has had the fortune to <hi>Courſe</hi> the <hi>Hare</hi> and catch the <hi>Witch.</hi> He miſtakes his <hi>Fool</hi> and his <hi>Game:</hi> And well remembred, <hi>Wiſe man of</hi> Gotham, how the <hi>Scot tuke the Tartar,</hi> and the <hi>Tartar</hi> prov'd the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might have dwelt longer upon his <hi>Title-page,</hi> ſufficiently anſwer'd him, and never have gone farther than the <hi>Porch:</hi> But curioſity prompts me to ſhew his <hi>Gueſts</hi> what better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment or <hi>welcome</hi> they and I muſt be treated with in the <hi>Houſe.</hi> At the <hi>Threſhold</hi> then I ſhall only premiſe a groſs injury done me, and ſoberly <hi>good morrow</hi> his paſſionate ELDERSHIPS ſcandals and miſconſtructions of me: For in my <hi>Remarks</hi> or <hi>Reflections,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 12.</note> (which I allow him to take in the <hi>worſt ſenſe</hi>) on his <hi>Obſervations,</hi> I fully declared my <hi>propo's</hi> and <hi>deſign,</hi> which he has run <hi>Counter</hi> to with a <hi>full cry,</hi> almoſt throughout his <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> only coldly <hi>chopping</hi> on't here and there. The <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grel-hound</hi> often flings off and runs a <hi>back-ſcent;</hi> But a worſe <hi>Noſe</hi> than his might have taken the <hi>right Game</hi> and made a truer <hi>chaſe</hi> of it: A <hi>falſe purſuit</hi> never obtain'd the leaſt <hi>Quarry.</hi> Having waved the <hi>Divinity</hi> of his <hi>King-killing,</hi> and traducing <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> let the <hi>unbiaſs'd</hi> Judge, if it is fair play to be bid <hi>keep cloſe to the Text, — ho! Religion</hi> is the Province of our Learned <hi>Clergy;</hi> there were eleven <hi>Apoſtles</hi> for one <hi>Judas;</hi> and we have <hi>Orthodox Divines</hi> enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute his <hi>Schiſmatical Doctrine,</hi> though too many follow their <hi>Maſter,</hi> like <hi>Peter,</hi> at a diſtance in ſecular Perſecutions; and it is well if more do not <hi>deny</hi> him: In all <hi>Don Quevedo</hi>'s Viſions <hi>Judas</hi> was the only Man in Hell for <hi>ſelling</hi> his <hi>God;</hi> but there was a <hi>number</hi> for <hi>buying</hi> of HIM. But I never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to meddle with thoſe <hi>matters that were too high for me,</hi> or handling of <hi>Controverſies</hi> in Religion, which required an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Pen.</hi> I have often thought of the Story of the ſilly <hi>Aſs</hi> that carryed the <hi>Goddeſs Iſis</hi> ſo long to and from the <hi>Temple,</hi> that at laſt he began to take <hi>State</hi> upon him, and would needs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174404:7"/>play the <hi>Goddeſs:</hi> So I have gone a long time to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by Law Eſtabliſhed, and I never yet could call the Preacher <hi>God Almighty's Spiritual Merry Andrew,</hi> or the Lecturer <hi>Gods after-noon Jeſter;</hi> A Libertine or Atheiſt may banter his Soul, and jeſt with his Salvation: I never thought the <hi>Miniſter</hi> in the Surplice an <hi>Owl in an Ivy Buſh,</hi> as <hi>Iſlington Cook</hi> had it in the days of <hi>Oliver's Goſpel.</hi> And I do not yet ſee any reaſon for <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Diſſention.</hi> Neither am I able to be the tottering <hi>Churches Atlas,</hi> nor to <hi>Sampſon</hi> it down with the ſtrength of Conviction and Diviſion. Believe me, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formling,</hi> I am in the ſame humour with the modeſt <hi>Lay-Countrey man,</hi> who coming up to <hi>London</hi> did not aſpire to a <hi>Mitre,</hi> or think to ſet his <hi>Foot</hi> at next <hi>ſtep</hi> of Preferment upon St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far you ſee the <hi>Front</hi> of our <hi>Juſt, Sober</hi> and <hi>Wiſe</hi> VINDICATOR, yet <hi>enter,</hi> and his <hi>Inner Rooms</hi> are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Furniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At firſt Salute he begins like a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> opens his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, and <hi>declares</hi> as it were for a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> The Mountain is in labour, and <hi>naſcitur</hi> Sooterkin. Ridiculous!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>I not out of any peeviſh humour</hi> — and the <hi>Verb,</hi> his great AUXILIARY, <hi>have taken the freedom</hi> — comes trotting in jaded ſeven or eight <hi>lines,</hi> I had like to have ſaid, MILES, behind: His words of <hi>Truth and Soberneſs</hi> hang-an-arſe too in the mid-way to the journeys period, and ſeem unwilling to come up to his <hi>undefiled Worſhip,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi> But he hath found out a <hi>ſore</hi> about me, and hath an Hoſpital for the Wounded on the <hi>firſt floor,</hi> if the Patient will not <hi>ſtart,</hi> take wing or <hi>fly out;</hi> as if he were about curing a <hi>Butter-fly,</hi> which <hi>Domitian</hi> had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifully <hi>run up to the Hilts:</hi> nor make a <hi>noiſe,</hi> while he han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles and probes the <hi>unſoundneſs;</hi> as if he were about to ſalve the crackt <hi>pericranium of a Waſp</hi> in a Honey-pot. Let him reſolve to cruſh the Cockatrice-Egg of his own hatching, leſt in the end it prove a <hi>hiſſing Scrpent</hi> to himſelf. The <hi>Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mater</hi> of his own Brain ſtands in need of the <hi>Phyſician;</hi> and I wiſh the ſame <hi>Gentleman Chirurgeon</hi> would be ſenſible of his own Errors, and ſo become <hi>Achillean</hi> to cure the Wounds, which himſelf hath made in our Church and State.</p>
            <p>In the next place are his <hi>Combuſtibles:</hi> Room enough for the Fire of <hi>Foxes Tails,</hi> which ſhall do no more harm than in <hi>Judges</hi> 15. <hi>Chapter.</hi> I wonder to ſee him ſo much in love
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174404:8"/>with <hi>Foxes and Fire-brands;</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Book called ſo.</note> our burned Child dreads not the Fire. He would <hi>pun</hi> a Man to Death, and the ſhades of Ghoſts almoſt with <hi>Lovaliſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 22.</note> LOYOLIST, to derive me from <hi>LOYOLA,</hi> a few <hi>ap's</hi> from a Helliſh Pedigree: But I will aſſure him the POPE is none of my <hi>Soveraign Lord,</hi> though ſuch as <hi>J. G. G.</hi> are <hi>Ignatians, (i.e.)</hi> Fire-brands to all the World beſide: <hi>Rome</hi> may well laugh at the <hi>Grinder</hi> when ſhe has the <hi>Griſt:</hi> Neither do I think <hi>Martial</hi>'s rule an axiom for my Pen — <hi>Parcere perſonis dicere de vitiis.</hi> For I look upon the ſly <hi>Jeſuite</hi> and <hi>Barge-ſainted Fanatick,</hi> with my own as well as <hi>anothers Eye,</hi> as two <hi>dangerous Philiſtine Foxes,</hi> that carry between their Tails that Brand of confuſion — <hi>The Lawful depoſition of Supream Magiſtrates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hill <hi>at</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge <hi>prayed —Depoſc him, O Lord, who would D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſe us.</hi> Aſſem. Man. p. 14.</note> If their <hi>Faces</hi> be contrary, they are coupled by the <hi>Tails,</hi> and although they may not tug with the ſame <hi>Oar;</hi> Their Faces look one way againſt <hi>White-hall</hi> and <hi>Lambeth:</hi> it is no great matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they Row and are bound for <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Geneva-hey!</hi> Here he plays the <hi>Doctor</hi> upon me again with <hi>capouring</hi> and <hi>vapou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of the <hi>Spleen and low parts, which cauſe great fumes and diſturbances in the Head:</hi> And are the <hi>Natural</hi> Members then ſubject to the <hi>Higher Powers?</hi> Would he be willing that his <hi>Head ſhould ake</hi> till he profeſſed this <hi>politically?</hi> If he will agree to't; the <hi>Colledge</hi> ſurely muſt make much of him for his new Invention, and honour him like <hi>Harvey for a Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> The <hi>Government</hi> ſhould call him good <hi>Subject,</hi> ſtroak him, and buy him <hi>Monumental Ginger-bread,</hi> as <hi>Clieveland</hi> uſes the <hi>Rebel Scot.</hi> Oh! that he could be <hi>clawed</hi> into a retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Noll</hi>'s Arts and Practices, that he would <hi>pur</hi> and <hi>pur</hi> while we rub off his Old <hi>Mange!</hi> Then we ſhould hear no ſuch ſcrieking and <hi>catter-wauling</hi> againſt our Church-Order. But I am afraid Sir <hi>Empirick Presbyter</hi> underſtands not the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Pulſe,
<note place="margin">Vena Baſilica.</note> nor the <hi>Baſilick-vein</hi> to make a <hi>Politick Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> and will be working upon the <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> Humours, till he waſts and conſumes the very <hi>Vitals.</hi> What ſignifies this among Friends? The Quack and the Sexton are <hi>Cater-Couſins</hi> ſtill, if one can but <hi>kill</hi> as faſt as the other cuts out <hi>Oblivion for the Murder.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1.14.</note> Acts of Parliament will <hi>perpetuate Diviſions,</hi> elſe the <hi>Reformling</hi> means nothing by laying that ſcandal at the <hi>Parſons Door</hi> for Preaching on the <hi>Anniverſaries</hi> of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Murder, the bleſſing of Peace and Right; for <hi>nothing</hi> and <hi>nothing</hi> to purpoſe in every <hi>Ninnys Logick</hi> is all one; the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174404:8"/>Saddle on the right Aſs is this; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of it; we keep up a <hi>Church</hi> by Law againſt the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and till we line their Purſes with her Revenues and <hi>Equipe</hi> 'em with <hi>Cloaks</hi> out of our <hi>Veſtiary,</hi> they are reſolved never to Unite or Mount our Altar, Baptiſtery or Pulpit, for they cannot ride <hi>Triumphantly</hi> elſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 66.</note> and we ſhall never be eaſed of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, din, or eternal <hi>Clack</hi> of their diſſenting Faction. That our <hi>Anniverſary</hi> Faſt and Thankſgiving chiefly diſguſts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues, or <hi>perpetuates</hi> their diviſion and Schiſm, I will believe, when I ſee them throw their <hi>Carolus a Carolo</hi> Money out of their <hi>Pockets,</hi> and hold it Superſtitition to carry <hi>Britania</hi>'s <hi>Picture</hi> about them. If the <hi>Reformling</hi> can give me one <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> of the Truth of <hi>Paracelſus</hi>'s Doctrine—<hi>That to eat Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alive will perpetuate Mans Life:</hi> I may probably be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſwallow a leſs abſurdity, that our <hi>Anniverſary Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> wherein in the <hi>Creature</hi> (his Dialect) is no otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, than as a Heinous Sin was committed and a providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al bleſſing was beſtowed upon HIM, does occaſion immortal <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which he Engliſhes <hi>perpetuate Diviſions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 37.</note> I am amaz'd to hear the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of Preaching,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 42.</note> the blackeſt Rebellion <hi>down</hi> to its <hi>Grand-fire,</hi> and right re-inthroned, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice reſtored <hi>up</hi> to the King of Kings, controverted by any but the Imps and <hi>Zanies</hi> of Infernal Empire. This is the all of our Worſhip on the <hi>Royal Anniverſaries,</hi> and yet diſſenting obſtinacy ſays, we may as ſoon meet upon a <hi>needleſs Point</hi> as this, or center in Union: We neither pray to, for, nor againſt the Souls ſeparate of our Kings; God is the Author and ſole Object of our Devotions.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>Truth</hi> may as well be ſaid to <hi>Lie</hi> as rail in our Sermons on the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> and Twenty ninth of <hi>May,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 13.</note> which his contradictious ſpirit calls <hi>Seditious;</hi> but he hits himſelf no ſmall <hi>Fillip</hi> there. And in ſhort, there is leſs mixture of the <hi>Creature</hi> in our occaſional Worſhip, than the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> had in his Comical <hi>Grace,</hi> wherein he begged a bleſſing upon the <hi>Turky-pie, for though it be no Chriſtian Fowl,</hi> ſays he, <hi>yet thou haſt commanded us to pray for all Jews, TURKS, Infidels and Hereticks.</hi> As another <hi>Graces</hi> it in complaiſance to his <hi>Fare; Souſe us and dowſe us in the powdering-tub of Repentance, and make us fit Tripes and Chitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for thy Heavenly Table.</hi> Strange! How ſome <hi>Capricio's</hi> hugg their ſingularity in that Monumental ſin of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> not thinking the <hi>Witchcraft</hi> will leave them at the <hi>Gallows:</hi> The
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174404:9"/>Devil never hugg'd the <hi>Witch</hi> upon any other ſcore; and if the impenitent <hi>Rebel</hi> ſlips his <hi>Collar,</hi> Old Nick's an Aſs. My whole drift <hi>before</hi> was to rub this <hi>Tetter,</hi> and the worſe it ſpreads in his <hi>Vindication.</hi> But hold, I task my ſelf too far with <hi>Religion;</hi> and if our <hi>Reformling</hi> be a <hi>Lay-man</hi> as well as I am, for he's <hi>Plato's Servant</hi> to my knowledge: He is an impertinent <hi>Beaſt of reaſon,</hi> and as <hi>Coltiſh</hi> to take this Religious Controverſie upon him, as <hi>Nero's Brute</hi> was in State with the <hi>Conſulſhip.</hi> Every <hi>Wood</hi> will not make a <hi>Mercury:</hi> A judicious foreſight of the Heathens: For had he been <hi>touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood;</hi> ſince we had a <hi>ſmoaking</hi> World, the <hi>Tobacco Funker</hi> would not have ſtuck to have lighted his Pipe with a <hi>Finger of the God.</hi> But every uppiſh Conventicler can ſet up for a <hi>Profeſſor of Divinity;</hi> and were the Bugbear Epithet REGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>US kickt out of the Schools, J. G. G were as fit a Man as hath ſprung from the Loyns of <hi>Calvin</hi> to domineer a republican <hi>Moderator.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sermon at</hi> Pauls Croſs 25. <hi>November.</hi>
               </note> No woonder then, as the ingenious <hi>Henry</hi> King obſerved 1621. <q rend="margQuotes">If Preaching may breed ſurfeits that ſo many Crudities lie in the ſtomack <hi>of the People;</hi> that ſo many Fumes and giddy Vapours fly up into the head, to the no ſmall diſturbance of the Churches quiet; that ſo many hot ſpirits, like the Canons overcharged, recoyle againſt all Diſcipline, break into divers Factions, and with the <hi>Splints</hi> of thoſe crackt opinions, do more miſchief then Deliberation or Juſtice can ſuddenly ſalve.</q> I ſpeak no new unheard Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. This Community of Preaching hath brought it into ſuch cheap <hi>rate</hi> and contempt, with many, that, as if the gift of Tongues were proſtitute to Idiots, and Trades; you ſhall have a ſort of Lay Mechanick Presbyters of both Sexes <hi>(Praedicatores &amp; Praedicantiſſae)</hi> preſume too far upon their acquaintance with the Pulpit, that they will venture upon an expoſition, or undertake to manage a long unweildy Prayer conceived on the ſudden, though not ſo ſuddenly uttered; nay, they are ſo deſperate, they will torment a Text, and in their reſty Conventicles Teach as boldly, as if they were as well able to become Journey-men to the Pulpit, as to their own Trades.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Predeſtination, Election, and Reprobation,</hi> they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 11, 19.</note> Good and Gracious words, but no ſuch Myſteries, as our <hi>Reformling</hi> miſunderſtands and miſinterprets; and although I do not <hi>ſport</hi> with the Tremendous and Eternal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174404:9"/>Decrees of Heaven, yet <q rend="margQuotes">I can whiſtle at his Heavenly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Bag-pipes,</hi> and look upon ſuch inquiſitive record ſearchers of the Supreme Judge, but as bold Aſtrologers, who ſaucily and preſumptuouſly pretend to bring intelligence from the <hi>Privy Council</hi> of Heaven, as if they had pickt the Cabinet of Fate and Providence through the <hi>Key-hole</hi> of the Stars. The <hi>Dutch-man</hi> found himſelf in the <hi>wrong Box</hi> at laſt, and ſwore there was no <hi>Butter</hi> there.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You are ſcarce ſooner <hi>entered</hi> the Glorious Fabrick of his contriving Brain, but whip he goes, as nimble as a <hi>Monkey,</hi> to the Houſe-top, and as ſwift as <hi>exhalations from the Earth,</hi> he's rapt and tranſported with <hi>Thunder</hi> and <hi>Lightning,</hi> many <hi>Stories</hi> above <hi>Bedlam Garrets,</hi> into the ſecond <hi>Region of the Air:</hi> But the <hi>Storm ceaſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 2.</note> and down comes he like <hi>gentle Snow</hi> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. to Boil <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Pot with the crackling of Thorns,</hi> as if he had ſtolen 'em from the <hi>Man in the Moon.</hi> This is his Vagarie; and I leave my <hi>Incerti Laris</hi> — Friend to maunder here and <hi>Cook</hi> by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>His next <hi>Paragraph</hi> couples him with the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> and I ſhall anſwer them in the <hi>leaſh.</hi> As they come in my <hi>way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I am for them, armed with reaſon, not <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Piſtol:</hi> For a Man may as ſoon beat Religion, as good Manners into either Head with a <hi>Pole-axe;</hi> and therefore I would not have them cry out <hi>Murther</hi> with ſuch a falſe <hi>hollow!</hi> Sure, had our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formling</hi> been an <hi>Antidiluvian,</hi> he would have cryed out Fire, Fire luſtily, in <hi>Noah's Flood.</hi> As <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> ſhine by turns, ſo they muſt ever expect an <hi>alternate</hi> extinction. Take care of your <hi>Candles</hi> both, elſe for the glimmerings of your reaſon, you may walk Home with the fainter light of a <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm. Though the Pamphlet in Queſtion, be not in any thing worth a reply, and the Pamphleteer deſerves to be anſwered other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then with a Pen;</hi> a Pen, Man! what can be a better ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, except his <hi>Cudgel</hi> or <hi>Kill-zadock,</hi> and convincing <hi>Club-law?</hi> Here I might eat his words, as he often does mine, and retort, it were a ſufficient <hi>Reyonder.</hi> But he mercifully <hi>leaves me to my Competent Judge,</hi> p. 7. Did not his own hand <hi>ſhake</hi> when he wrote, JUDGE? His own guilt might very well have given him the <hi>Palſie.</hi> This <hi>Sentence</hi> he borrows from the <hi>Weekly Obſervator,</hi> and publiſhes himſelf a <hi>Plagiary</hi> in his <hi>Poſtſcript:</hi> And for all our <hi>Reformling</hi>'s different Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174404:10"/>of Religions, they are much of the ſame <hi>Feature:</hi> I leave the Devil and the Colliar to parley whether had the blacker Complexion. Now ſince he does ſtand upon the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Legs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 73.</note> for the Support and Authority of his illegal Obſervations, he ſhall <hi>ſeem to be as good a Man</hi> as he pleaſes, but then he muſt acknowledge himſelf, <hi>to be very much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſeveral of his Notions, and eſpecially in Church Ceremonies:</hi> And ſo he gives up his Cauſe, and looſes his <hi>Tub</hi> as the <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> loſt his <hi>Knife,</hi> which he had all the while between <hi>his Teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As never any Beauty or fair Face, gained all Hearts their ſuffrages or admiration; nor any ingenuity and <hi>plain-dealing</hi> a general applauſe: So there hath ſeldom been wanting an <hi>Apologiſt</hi> to refute the pittiful and paultry Imputations of the <hi>reflector.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 12.</note> An <hi>Author</hi> now a days has no civiler treatment than a <hi>Piſſing-poſt;</hi> every little <hi>Cur</hi> holds up his Leg at him, cocks his Tail, and throws dirt in his Face. As I ſhould have the ſtomack of a <hi>Night-man</hi> to read <hi>Tartaretus de more cacandi;</hi> ſo truly I would as ſoon chooſe to be condemned to be a <hi>Scavenger</hi> for the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> and to carry all the Dung out of this little World of <hi>Sin and Sea-Goal,</hi> as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the <hi>foul</hi> and <hi>filthy</hi> abſurdities of the <hi>Reformer,</hi> or the mercenary Scandals of the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> more then I have or ſhall do, in ſhort. A <hi>Muckender</hi> for 'em both to rake their <hi>puddles</hi> of reproach.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reformling</hi> wreſts, culls, and tears my <hi>Book</hi> in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed Mood for Forty and more <hi>Pages</hi> together, as if he had never drawn bit nor breath for't; and he makes the verieſt <hi>Tatter de mallion</hi> of it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 13.</note> with <hi>half words</hi> and <hi>half ſentences,</hi> that it would certainly cry for the <hi>Rag-man,</hi> but that it had been at the <hi>Paper-mill</hi> already. He hath the <hi>bien tourne,</hi> I'le ſay't, at marring of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and as excellent a knack of a <hi>Laconick</hi> anſwer, as a <hi>Popiſh Prieſt</hi> in the late times, who, Preaching in a Chappel about Town,
<note place="margin">Reported by Biſhop—</note> brought a <hi>petit Library</hi> of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical reformed Authors with him, and told the Auditory with a brisk look, he muſt confute them; the firſt he touch'd upon chanced to be <hi>John Calvin:</hi> This is that grand Enemy to our Church, <hi>John Calvin,</hi> ſays he; his firſt word is <hi>Inſtitutiones,</hi> gives him a quick <hi>turn-over,</hi> his laſt word is <hi>Iniquitates.</hi> His <hi>Inſtitutiones</hi> are <hi>Iniquitates,</hi> ye may <hi>conclude</hi> with himſelf, and ſo he lays him by with <hi>confutation</hi> enough to his <hi>Hearers.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:174404:10"/>So <hi>J. G. G.</hi> picks out words, ſtrips them of all antecedent and conſequent Senſe, and when he has them <hi>naked,</hi> he whips them off with a <hi>Jerque.</hi> Thus <hi>Atheiſm</hi> ſhall be proved out of Scripture; the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> has it — <hi>There is no God;</hi> not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what went before, <hi>The Fool hath ſaid it in his Heart:</hi> For who but a <hi>Fool</hi> would have ſaid ſo? He rakes up an <hi>Oglio</hi> of a few ſcattered words <hi>Higlede-piglede</hi> in my expreſſions; and then he Mauls, and Slanders, and Rogues them <hi>ad arbitrium;</hi> as the <hi>Cock-bawd</hi> will be beſpattering the <hi>Carted-whore</hi> of his own making; though of all Men in the World he ſhould not caſt the <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Horns</hi> at her. As Diviſion is his Talent he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it upon my ſenſe and words to his own <hi>Note.</hi> He ſhatters the whole Frame of my Diſcourſe to <hi>pieces,</hi> like the ſplinters of the <hi>Knight Errant's Lance:</hi> But he breaks no <hi>Bones,</hi> but what being <hi>ſet</hi> by an unprejudiced Hand, will knit more firmly and ſtrong againſt him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 4.</note> For my <hi>abuſive and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Language</hi> I had his <hi>parol</hi> that he would not <hi>take advantage of the Law Talionis</hi> upon it, but it is ſo material a <hi>Limb of Magna Charta,</hi> that he muſt now ſtand upon it as a piece of priviledge to quit ſcores with me: And the fundamental conſtitution of <hi>Billingſgate</hi> is — <hi>You're a Rogue, and you're a Rogue.</hi> This is his <hi>Religion,</hi> which cannot govern his <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> and ſuch an one, <q rend="margQuotes">is not a Dram better than my Maſtiff Dog, ſo long as you ſtroke him and pleaſe him, and do not pinch him, he will play with you as finely as may be, <hi>and wag his Tail:</hi> He is a very good Moral Maſtiff; but if you hurt him, he will fly in your Face, and tear out your Throat, ſays <hi>Selden</hi> p. 36.</q> Where Scripture ſhould ſhackle his <hi>hot-ſpur</hi> ſpirit, he breaks forth <hi>pell-mell</hi> upon me; and calls me Fool, and Fool, and Fool, to the end of the Chapter. He would turn me a <hi>grazing</hi> to converſe with none but <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi>'s Society. <hi>pag.</hi> 4. certainly he does not wiſh me his <hi>Metamorphoſe</hi> too, of long <hi>Nails</hi> for fear of a <hi>Scratch't Face.</hi> I am a <hi>Lion</hi> in his <hi>Roaring</hi> pag. 31. that would have all under a ſpoiling <hi>Paw;</hi> yes, when he is my <hi>Jackal</hi> I ſhall never want Prey. All along he inſinuates me to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> a furious <hi>Perſecutor.</hi> pag. 6. <hi>That would promote the Ruin and Conſuſion of Kingdoms with Fire and Fagot.</hi> This is his <hi>Ignis fatuus:</hi> Such wild-fire does not burn; and it's all made by the <hi>antiperiſtaſis</hi> of his own <hi>clod pate, Neroe's Fiddle</hi> would have ſounded harſh to my Ear in the combuſtion of blazing <hi>Rome;</hi> and I could
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174404:11"/>have wiſhed, when <hi>London</hi> was of a Flame, that the Fire had not lookt and rag'd ſo much like the Final conflagration; that it had been no greater, no fiercer, than what any Man might have <hi>piſſed out.</hi> What a pother and <hi>calenture</hi> were the Brains of that Hyper-critical Philoſopher in, to find out the Materials <hi>God firſt ſtruck Light with?</hi> I pity the nice folly, but I hold, and practice according to my Tenet, that <hi>fire</hi> was not made to blow up <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or to ſerve either a <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian Plot.</hi> I ſhould have been content never to have ſeen <hi>Englands</hi> Wonder, a <hi>Monument</hi> erected upon the aſhes of our Metropolis: Oh! that every Mans <hi>Engine</hi> could have quenched the Flames; and fewer Tears then were ſhed might have put them out! I do not think <hi>King Charles II.</hi> brought the <hi>Goal</hi> or the <hi>Incendiary</hi> home with him, as he would intimate in his <hi>Obſervations</hi> p. 13, 14. Neither do I believe it was for the Sin of <hi>Gluttony,</hi> though the Fire began in <hi>Pudding-Lane</hi> and ended in <hi>Pye-Corner:</hi> The Heavens have ſpent much Fire and Brimſtone in Old Story, upon Murder, Rebellion and Faction. He hints at my <hi>Dear Siſter Popery</hi> again <hi>pag.</hi> 18. when I deny the Relation or Affinity; and was never wedded yet ſo far to any <hi>Religion,</hi> but upon good Evidence and true Conviction I might be <hi>Divorced. Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiſm and Popery are his Darlings,</hi> Ibid. The laſt time we ſhak'd Hands with <hi>Popery</hi> I bid it a <hi>Farewell</hi> with all my Heart.
<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>A liar, a Child of the Devil, a falſe accuſer,</hi> that is, the Devil's Devil, as <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> was ſaid to Poſſeſs Satan, not Satan <hi>Hugh Peters. The Proteſtant Cauſe is perfidiouſly betrayed by me, pag.</hi> 68. He may Trumpet this with a <hi>Silver Tongue</hi> to be neither impious, nor prophane, nor ſcurrilous, nor perfidious, but I muſt tell him, his <hi>Fore-head</hi> is of the ſame Metal with his <hi>Kitchin,</hi> if there is any <hi>Braſs</hi> in it, for doing ſo. <hi>A Villain,</hi> page 65. <hi>an Arminian,</hi> page 66. <hi>a Cut-throat, an Executioner, a Hangman,</hi> page 15, 34. <hi>I arraign God for his Decree,</hi> page 57. <hi>Mentiris impudentiſſime,</hi> page 70. and his own Engliſh of it. —<hi>Thou art a moſt impudent liar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quid pro quo.</note> is a pretty conciſe anſwer to all that he hath ſcandalouſly <hi>held forth.</hi> For <hi>Uniformity-ſake</hi> we muſt <hi>hang together,</hi> page 34. He gives me all the <hi>Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s <hi>Office,</hi> but wheres the <hi>Gallows? Haman</hi> made a <hi>Gallows</hi> for another, and was Hang'd on it himſelf. What a <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game</hi> he makes of an <hi>Act of Parliawent</hi> with his <hi>Uniformity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twang?</hi> He little conſiders ſurely, how his jeſt intrenches upon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174404:11"/>the old <hi>Round-head</hi> Cant, <hi>Good Lord, make us of one Accord, Concord, Record, or Any-Cord, Good Lord, that we may hang all together;</hi> and a bold daring <hi>Cavalier</hi> ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to't. But I would <hi>ſtab him if I could,</hi> pag. 14. I never puſh home a Topick with the <hi>Rhetorick of the Sword:</hi> I write with ſuch <hi>Ink</hi> as He does, not with <hi>Blood;</hi> for Sanguinary Laws I am averſe to, yet I do not think or eſteem DRACO the worſe Lawgiver for His. Indeed to be called ſo many Names, would make a Man ſcratch where it does not itch, as CHAUCER has it upon <hi>another Account:</hi>
               <note place="margin">To ſee Men live poor to dye rich.</note> I care not what the <hi>Italians</hi> ſay; but I wonder he ſhould travel ſo far for an <hi>Itch of a Popiſh Expreſſion,</hi> pag. 16. He's a great <hi>Linguiſt,</hi> I ſuppoſe; for he ſays <hi>Latin</hi> is the <hi>Language of the Beaſt,</hi> pag. 23. But it would certainly be worth his Enquiry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Balaam's Aſs ſpoke Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Language is abuſive, unbecoming, immodeſt, unclean, ridiculous, reviling, impious, injurious, rubbiſh, traſh, and ſtuff. — Well ſaid <hi>Textor!</hi> So he <hi>haſhes</hi> it, and makes ſuch a <hi>Hotch-potch Sluttery</hi> of it, that, like the <hi>Greedy gut who ſpit in his porridge,</hi> he deſigns it all for himſelf. Enter <hi>Obſervator.</hi> The <hi>Painter</hi> that ſhould put a <hi>Pen</hi> into the <hi>Angel</hi>'s hand would detract from his Knowledge, and <hi>degrade Intuition.</hi> But were it no <hi>Groteſque,</hi> and if Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wrote <hi>Books,</hi> I am apt to think we ſhould not have fewer <hi>Mercury</hi>'s: and their happieſt Notions would hardly eſcape the Libelling, Cenſure, and <hi>Burleſque</hi> of a braving <hi>Obſervator.</hi> How nobly would <hi>Grubſtreet</hi> encounter Heaven and cry out upon the <hi>abuſive language</hi> of Thunder, and the Nonſenſe of Flaſhes and Lightnings for foul play in the Quarrel!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 7.</note> were the <hi>pacifick Angels</hi> to converſe with <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians:</hi> for I am ſo charitable as not to wiſh the <hi>deſtroying</hi> ones among them; in order to proſelite ſo many perſecuting <hi>Sauls</hi> of our Church. Were they commiſſioned to make them loyal and pious Converts by conforming them to our <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Liturgy;</hi> would not one believe that the main ſtreſs and argument of their <hi>Revelation</hi> would be urged from the Novelty, Inhumanity, and Unchriſtian Cruelty of their King-killing or Schiſmatical Principles and Zealous Biggoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm? Which in the Language of <hi>Man,</hi> were to call them, the <hi>Diſſenters, Schiſmaticks,</hi> and <hi>Regicides.</hi> Where is the Harſhneſs or Impiety of the Dialect then? To call a Man
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174404:12"/>an Eternal <hi>Villain</hi> whoſe Ears bear witneſs of the Cruelty, if he pleaſes, or Juſtice of the <hi>Pillory,</hi> and have eternized his Fame, can be no great Abuſe, I hope, or unjuſt Affront. You cannot take the <hi>Sow</hi> by the wrong Ear when ſhe has <hi>none</hi> left. <hi>O Edipodas facito, Telegonoſque voces,</hi> ſays <hi>Ovid of his Amourettes;</hi> he bids his <hi>Triſtia</hi> call 'em Rogues and Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals: <hi>OEdipus</hi>'s and <hi>Telegonus</hi>'s, Murderers.</p>
            <p>And may not an artificial height of Paſſion be allowed in an <hi>Orator</hi> as well as the ſweet-tongu'd <hi>Poet?</hi> He's not the leſs mild and <hi>ſoft</hi> for a Counterfeit-Anger: for He only ſung a feigned Chaſtiſement of his <hi>de Arte amandi</hi> Adventures, which He yet lov'd ſo far, I dare ſay, as to pride Himſelf in Baniſhment for innocent Wit and Amour. No; this is not allowable: it is <hi>abuſive.</hi> Why? for what Reaſon but a Woman's? Becauſe it is. Or an <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s IPSE DIXIT? The notable Panſophiſt hath ſaid ſo. Methinks a little Senſe and leſs Wit might diſtinguiſh the <hi>Perſons</hi> from their <hi>Good Old Cauſe:</hi> I can love the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> and hate his <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance;</hi> What! <hi>Not one penny left of five hundred a year?</hi> Have <hi>Charity</hi> for the <hi>Rebel,</hi> and abominate the <hi>Rebellion;</hi> the Vicious Perſon and the Vice are diſtinguiſhable by an eaſie <hi>Logick,</hi> and I think the Tongue may ſtab a baſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple through and through the ſides of a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and the patient Perſon be ne're the worſe hurt. A ſort of humour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome people are labouring with a <hi>Ic ne ſcay que</hi> of a ſingular Diſtemper and Ruptures of their own making; well, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſives</hi> are applied, and the Wound probed deep in order to a ſafer Cure: The Patient groans under the tart Remedy; in comes Sir <hi>Empirick,</hi> and calls the Phyſician <hi>abuſive:</hi> A wonderful Quack-aſſurance and Judgment indeed! I'll war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you <hi>Presbytery</hi> is not to be handled but with ſuch a comprehenſive <hi>Wafer-Charity</hi> as His: the <hi>Wafer</hi> is eaſily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the leaſt <hi>dry touch,</hi> and then the whole <hi>Bond</hi> of Chriſtian Love is <hi>cancelled</hi> and nullified. If he opinions that <hi>Presbytery</hi> cannot endure the Teſt and <hi>Touch</hi> of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, he will bring it into the like Suſpicion and Diſgrace with the ſalivated <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s tender Noſe, that had got the <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> and could not abide the Jeſt of a <hi>Naſo ſuſpendere adunco:</hi> who ſlightly made uſe of his <hi>Handkerchief,</hi> and wip'd off the angry <hi>Bow ſpreat</hi> of his Face into his Pocket, becauſe it ſhould be no longer the Subject of a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174404:12"/>pockify'd Bantre or <hi>Jeer.</hi> He that would be cured of the <hi>King's Evil,</hi> muſt have the <hi>Royal Touch;</hi> ſome perhaps had rather reſt <hi>incurable.</hi> A <hi>Presbyterian</hi> can no otherwiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>breach of Charity</hi> for a Reaſon why it ſhould not be <hi>touched</hi> with the ſevereſt Truths, than a <hi>Corps</hi> kept under ground ſeemingly entire, which being once touched, ſoon falls to duſt and aſhes. How ſtrange a Paradox, how mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous a Notion does he frame of Charity, Love, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, who would have the ſatyrical canvaſſing of <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Polity</hi> and the Invectives of Controverſie to be Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of <hi>Goſpel-Vertue!</hi> I would ask him but this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on civilly: Does he think Mr. <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Head might not be <hi>broken</hi> without <hi>breach of Charity?</hi> the one ſtand in need of a <hi>plaiſter,</hi> and the other not need the leaſt <hi>ſalvo?</hi> With <hi>Charity</hi> I hold the Affirmative: and I am ſure there is leſs <hi>blood</hi> drawn from laſhing their Principles and Opinions. What if I mean no <hi>Body</hi> or no individual, particularly? There are no <hi>broken pates</hi> among <hi>Univerſals:</hi> and he knows <hi>no Body breaks his windows at Foot-ball.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could my <hi>Pen</hi> write as deep a <hi>ſtyle</hi> and more legible Characters of Perjury, Diſloyalty, and Rebellion, than the Whip does, on the Backs of ſuch <hi>reſpective</hi> Malefactors at a <hi>Carts Arſe;</hi> I ſhould not think my ſelf the worſe <hi>Chriſtian</hi> for an <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s exclaiming, inhumane, uncharitable, <hi>abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Tory:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 6.</note> I have nothing to ſay but <hi>Sir William Coventry</hi> for the Trimmers; but to call <hi>Church-men</hi> highflown names is <hi>Billingſgate</hi> all over. I might have advertiſed them of a notable <hi>Petition</hi> of the <hi>moderate Divines</hi> drawn up by a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical <hi>Witling</hi> laſt Seſſion of Parliament — That the 30th of <hi>January</hi> and 29th of <hi>May</hi> be diſcarded out of <hi>Partridge</hi>'s Almanack, as being great Eye-ſores to the Godly Party; but they are <hi>reſolved</hi> for anotherguiſe <hi>Debate.</hi> Could the dint of <hi>Pen</hi> cry <hi>Slaſh,</hi> like the Whip, at every period: Law and Juſtice would <hi>authorize</hi> and juſtifie the <hi>Severities</hi> of the <hi>one</hi> with as much tender reaſon as the Slaſhes of the <hi>other,</hi> and no Law rightly interpreted, is repugnant to that of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity:</hi> ſo that the whole <hi>charge</hi> and burden of <hi>Nonſenſe and abuſive Language</hi> thrown at me, I am afraid, for all the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſity and bluff Moderation of an <hi>Obſervator,</hi> will <hi>recoil</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that firſt <hi>diſcharged</hi> the reviling <hi>Mouth-Granado.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:174404:13"/>
            <p>Perhaps it was a cruel Wiſh to have the <hi>Reformer</hi>'s Book burned: I can give him an old <hi>Rule</hi> for this Animoſity; <hi>Igne pereat qui fumum vendidit:</hi> and pity it ſhould be <hi>obſolete</hi> as long as ſuch <hi>Authors</hi> as he kindle thoſe <hi>Flames</hi> in their own Works, which ſhall conſume them; the ſilly <hi>Phaenix will be burning her own Neſt.</hi> For any thing I know his Friend <hi>Baldwin</hi> anticipated my Wiſh, to make his <hi>Book ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Palace-Yard,</hi> the <hi>Bookſeller</hi> knows, makes a thing Sell incomparably. I confeſs my Expreſſions were ſometimes <hi>troubled</hi> and ſtorming, ſometimes <hi>ſerene,</hi> calm and moderate. Here my Words fall like <hi>Hail,</hi> there like <hi>ſofter Snow;</hi> and with Mr. <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s leave and a ſhallow-brain'd <hi>Scioliſt's</hi> Favour, I rather judge it a piece of Art than a Fault or <hi>abuſive Language,</hi> to vary the <hi>Idea</hi> or Character of my Speech: now to ſmooth a Period, then to thunder, according to the quality of the Subject, and my ſatyrick Deſign on notorious Scandals: Scandals and Reproaches of two great, good, and juſt Kings! Their Fame is traduced: of our Church! Her Peace is diſquieted, and our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> rabbled by Sectaries into an Uproar of Diſſention. How liberal was <hi>Propertius</hi> in beſtowing his artful <hi>Curſes</hi> on the <hi>Baiae</hi> that kill'd <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi>'s Nephew! And where is the <hi>Abuſe</hi> or Imprudence in taunting <hi>thoſe</hi> with impaſſionated <hi>Satyr</hi> who kill'd <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf? <hi>Thoſe,</hi> whoſe Principles either oblige them to apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize for the heinous Fact, or to write it down to eternal Shades of Oblivion: <hi>Thoſe,</hi> who could frame a Panegyrick for <hi>Buſyris,</hi> a Vindication for <hi>Nero;</hi> with varniſhed Tenents, pleaſing Delirium's, Shifts and Diſguiſes, put ſuch a face on the Matter, as to accuſe Innocence, without guilt, of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny and Cruelty, Detraction and Inhumanity: <hi>Thoſe</hi> laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who would put all <hi>England</hi> into a doubt, not only to raiſe Vulgar Mens wonder, but to win a popular Belief, that what they called <hi>Juſtice</hi> was better executed on their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> than it had been if <hi>omitted.</hi> Here I ſhall take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for one Digreſſion on our <hi>Reformling</hi> pag. 28. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>St—ns,</hi> J. G. G. nor <hi>John A-ſtyles,</hi> are <hi>over-paſſionately concerned for King</hi> C.'s <hi>Death.</hi> Not over paſſionately; that is, in our Idiom, not <hi>paſſionately enough.</hi> They are <hi>Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>'s to day. King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reſtauration, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we, is to morrow; then they are <hi>Heraclitus</hi>'s. This is like the <hi>Saints Gibbriſh</hi> of <hi>Grantham.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 27.</note> Exceſs of Joy and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174404:13"/>Sorrow are equally dangerous: neither would I have Men revel till their Faces are all on Illuminations <hi>on this,</hi> nor weep into Funeral Marble <hi>on that occaſion.</hi> Paſſions are to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed when they riſe againſt reaſon: But the <hi>Moraliſt</hi> is not for rooting them out, but moderating them; we muſt not take away diverſity of Tunes in Muſick, but reduce 'em to good Order, and ſo make up a Harmony, till ſuch as our <hi>Reformling,</hi> I do not ſay <hi>Pigs,</hi> play upon <hi>Church Organs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 17.</note> Another Paradox is advanced, pag. 59. That <hi>thoſe who had been for the Parliament were the great Inſtruments in bringing King</hi> Charles 1. <hi>home again.</hi> It may be ſo: He that hath not ſo wiſe and worldling a Foreſight as to ſave his own <hi>Bacon,</hi> is the greater <hi>Hog</hi> of the two. The truth of it is not upon Record, and their ſubſequent Actions never verified the Report; for they were always <hi>nibling</hi> under-board at Kingly Power afterwards, and mouthing under the <hi>Roſe</hi> at Deſpotick Prerogative and Penal Laws. His <hi>Challenge</hi> to diſprove what he ſays of <hi>King Charles</hi> 2, pag. 13, 14. of his <hi>Obſervations,</hi> is huffing brave: It is more Honour to refuſe than accept ſuch Provocations; but I durſt diſpute it upon a <hi>Pillory</hi> with him, and he that loſt the Prize ſhould pay the <hi>Exciſe</hi> of his Ears or the <hi>Poll</hi> of his Head. However, he reproaches him; while his Miſcarriages as a <hi>Man</hi> ought to be obliterated in the Aſhes of Oblivion, and rak'd up in the Embers of an <hi>ardent</hi> and mutual Affection for his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as a good and peaceable and merciful <hi>King;</hi> for he might put all the <hi>Blood,</hi> he unlawfully ſpilt, in his Eye, and never ſee <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Indemnity</hi> the worſe for't. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Scripture bids him <hi>not Curſe,</hi> nor I preſume, revile, ſlander, traduce, <hi>the King in his Thought,</hi> he does it in <hi>Print,</hi> and ſaves the <hi>Letter</hi> of the Text: Becauſe Majeſty is <hi>ſacred,</hi> it muſt be <hi>prophaned</hi> with <hi>a private Reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Novel inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled ſo.</note> which thoſe of his <hi>Cabinet</hi> never knew any thing of: where he is <hi>falſly Romanced</hi> into the Murder of the <hi>Earl of Eſſex, Inceſt,</hi> and I know not what Aſperſions. Juſtly then hath Fancy given <hi>Satyr</hi> Teeth, and may they now bite like a <hi>Badger</hi>'s till they <hi>meet:</hi> What bad <hi>Decoctions</hi> of Stile muſt he <hi>ſtomach</hi> with, who in his undigeſted <hi>Rifts</hi> would call <hi>Sarcaſm,</hi> the very Purity and <hi>Nettetee</hi> of Rhetorick, <hi>abuſive Language?</hi> Nevertheleſs, ſays the high and mighty <hi>Obſervator: The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of</hi> The Reformer Rack'd <hi>has broken all bounds and rules of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174404:14"/>Humanity with Mankind; and perhaps never was there in a Pamphlet ſo much Nonſenſe and ſo much of abuſive Language as in this: But what can be expected from a Man, who in his ſecond Page looks upon Calviniſm as an Hereſie as damnable as Socinianiſm, Arrianiſm, and Anabaptiſm? Such a Champion of our Church deſerveth, I am ſure, to be taken notice of ſome other way than by an Obſervator; eſpecially if it has ſtolen out with no Licenſe from Authority, as I may reaſonably preſume it has.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Erroneous and Reviling <hi>Philiſtine</hi> is upon me, but the leaſt <hi>peble</hi> of an Argument drawn from clear Reaſon; Truth as <hi>naked</hi> and unarmed as <hi>David</hi> may humble or ſink into the <hi>Goliah</hi>'s Forehead and convince him, if he were more <hi>brazen'd</hi> than he is. How Magiſterially does he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce me in a <hi>State</hi> of War with Mankind? Let him be aſſured I am none of <hi>Hobbs's Creatures:</hi> though I think <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation</hi> is almoſt arrived at his pitch and <hi>ſtate</hi> of it; ſince I ſee moſt Men now a-days poſſeſſed with a ſpecious pretended neceſſity of <hi>Defence,</hi> where no <hi>Offence</hi> is half ſo much <hi>given</hi> as unfairly <hi>taken:</hi> and ſome are affrighted with <hi>Fantaſms,</hi> Fears, and Jealouſies of their own <hi>Wind-mill</hi> or <hi>Quixotian</hi> Fancies, ſtanding upon their own <hi>Guards</hi> never ſo unjuſtly. It would have made his Poſition good upon me to have proved every <hi>Swordſman</hi> that carries <hi>Toledo</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling at his ſide was in ſuch a Duelling Frolick, who never drew it in Anger or unſheathed for <hi>Inhumanity.</hi> The Pen was never yet reckoned a Weapon of War, but by the ſtrained <hi>Metaphor</hi> of a <hi>Paper-fight,</hi> or Writing-<hi>Combate. Exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enter <hi>Reformling</hi> pag. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. — The <hi>Reformer Rack'd</hi> was an unmerciful <hi>Title:</hi> yes, if I had miſconſtrued his Principles, or miſrepreſented his Vagaries; made him <hi>confeſs</hi> or depoſe Things upon that <hi>Titular Rack</hi> different from his Intentions or Perſwaſion, though he brings himſelf off, pag. 26. with the <hi>Equivocation of a Not Guilty King Charles</hi> 1. <hi>Racking</hi> is a hard Word: Suppoſe I had entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led my Pamphlet, <hi>The Reformer Booted and Thummakin'd:</hi> But the <hi>gude Covenant would na</hi> allow that <hi>miſleard Lownery, na, na, Billy.</hi> It muſt be a ſtrong Imagination that this <hi>Idea</hi> can extort a Sob or a Sigh from: A ſtout Malefactor may tremble at the Sight or Thought of the Three-legged <hi>Tree;</hi> but I never heard of any one that was <hi>choak'd</hi> with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174404:14"/>the <hi>Fancy.</hi> As for <hi>Reformation,</hi> I like nothing ſo ill in it indeed, as the NAME, and the <hi>Reformers.</hi> We know our Upſtart <hi>Reformling</hi> is as ſingular and prepoſſeſſed as he that would eat no <hi>Fiſh</hi> but what was taken out of the <hi>Lake of Geneva;</hi> that was the only reliſhing Fiſh for the <hi>Presbyterian Maw.</hi> I do not ſay <hi>Omnia bene:</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> might have reaſon to <hi>reform</hi> many Things in the <hi>Church,</hi> and had the ſole Supreme Authority to do it, howſoever <hi>ſhe</hi> might be adviſed. Will he grant this? <hi>Apud omnes Gentes, quaevis adminiſtratio ſolennis erat ſacerdotem, authoritas tamen ſumma ſanciendae, reformandae, vindicandae religionis, ſemper erat penes Magiſtratum. Reges Iſraelitici &amp; Chriſtiani idem jus ſibi ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicarunt, Davenant: Deter. quaeſt.</hi> 19. Exod. 31.18. And becauſe he falſly taxes me with Scripture-Ignorance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 60.</note> I ſhall humour him with another Text, <hi>Exod.</hi> c. 34.32, 34. Such as J. G. G. are not to be their own <hi>Carvers</hi> in a <hi>Reformation.</hi> But every <hi>Cot-Queen,</hi> that is ſcarce fit to make <hi>Kitchin-ſtuff,</hi> will have a finger in the <hi>Pye,</hi> and then it is not for my <hi>Tooth.</hi> Does he remember how long his <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> ſat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a <hi>new Religion,</hi> and in the <hi>interim</hi> left <hi>none</hi> at all. We had had a hopeful World on't, if the <hi>King of Arragon</hi> had been to aſſiſt <hi>God</hi> in the making of it; and yet the blaſphemous <hi>Architect</hi> thought he could have contrived it much better. The <hi>Giants</hi> built themſelves a very high <hi>Fall:</hi> and ſince our <hi>Reformling</hi> diſlikes <hi>Fables,</hi> he may love the <hi>Moral</hi> if he will. The Self-intereſt and <hi>Fat-livings</hi> of our <hi>Clergy,</hi> as he maligns them, retards a <hi>Reformation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 11.</note> O Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Intereſt! I can cry out againſt Intereſt as loud as he with his O's! and tell him that ſome <hi>Worthy Perſonages</hi> have gone through <hi>Traytor's Gate</hi> towards Heaven by the <hi>barbarous Intereſt</hi> of his <hi>Party.</hi> He may keep the Opinion of a <hi>Perfection in this Life</hi> to his <hi>Puritan-ſelf:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 10.</note> an Age is not enough for this Accompliſhment; but when ſeven years are run out, the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> may begin again and finiſh an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prenticeſhip</hi> as long as <hi>Life,</hi> yet come ſhort of that freedom and <hi>perfection</hi> they ſeek. Our <hi>Clergy</hi> would be ſtill impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Reformation:</hi> and it is not <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſo much as <hi>Schiſm</hi> that hinders, which has been ſo often baffled for all his <hi>new Challenge,</hi> that it gives ground and <hi>runs back</hi> to an Accommodation. Some have <hi>reformed</hi> out of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and to be ingenuous, whether <hi>Intereſt</hi> and a Pique did not ſet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174404:15"/>
               <hi>Luther's Reformation</hi> on foot, let <hi>Thuanus's Hiſtory</hi> of it be the <hi>Umpire.</hi> Let <hi>Eraſmus</hi> jeſt: <hi>Luther</hi> might have cracked a <hi>Creeper</hi> or beat a <hi>reforming Parley</hi> upon the <hi>Prieſts Belly</hi> with the <hi>Pope;</hi> but as far as I can impartially judge, the loſs of a little Intereſt more than a religious Diſlike, mov'd him to quarrel with <hi>Indulgences;</hi> as the Man that miſſed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>King's Treaſurer,</hi> began to rail at his <hi>Coin</hi> and the Revenues of the Crown. I ſubmit this Conjecture to the candid <hi>Reader</hi> of that Relation in the <hi>Council of Trent.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">The Occaſion was the Neceſſity of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, who by his Profuſion had ſo exhauſted the <hi>Treaſure</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> that he was conſtrained to have recourſe to the publiſhing of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> to raiſe Moneys: ſome of which he had deſtined to his own Treaſury, and other part to his Allies; and particularly to his <hi>Siſter,</hi> he gave all the Money that ſhould be raiſed in <hi>Saxony;</hi> and ſhe, that ſhe might make the beſt profit of the Donation, commits it to one <hi>Aremboldas,</hi> a Biſhop, to appoint Treaſurers for theſe Indulgences. Now the Cuſtom was, that whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever theſe Indulgences were ſent into <hi>Saxony,</hi> they were to be divulged by the Fryars <hi>Eremites,</hi> (of which Order <hi>Luther</hi> then was.) But <hi>Aremboldus</hi>'s Agents thinking with themſelves, that the Fryars <hi>Eremites</hi> were not ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Trade, that if the Buſineſs ſhould be leſt to them, they ſhould either be able to give ſo good an account of their Negotiation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Annotations upon Dr.</hi> Brown <hi>his</hi> Religio Medici.</note> or get ſo much themſelves by it as they might do in caſe the Buſineſs were committed to another Order; they therefore recommend it to (and the Buſineſs is undertaken by) the <hi>Dominican</hi> Fryars, who performed it ſo ill, that the Scandal ariſing both from thence, and from the ill Lives of thoſe that ſet them on work, ſtirred up <hi>Luther</hi> to write againſt the Abuſes of theſe Indulgences; which was all he did at firſt; but then not long after being provoked by ſome Sermons and ſmall Diſcourſes that had been publiſhed againſt what he had written, he rip; up the Buſineſs from the Beginning, and publiſhes XCV <hi>Theſes</hi> againſt it at <hi>Wittenberg.</hi> Againſt theſe <hi>Tekel</hi> a <hi>Dominican</hi> writes; then <hi>Luther</hi> adds an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to his. <hi>Eckins</hi> and <hi>Pierius,</hi> Dominicans, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon take up the Controverſie againſt him: and now <hi>Luther</hi> begins to be hot; and becauſe his Adverſaries
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174404:15"/>could not found the Matter of Indulgences upon other Foundations than the Pope's Power and Infallibility, that begets a Diſputation betwixt them concerning the Pope's Power, which <hi>Luther</hi> inſiſts upon as inferiour to that of a <hi>General Council;</hi> and ſo by degrees he came on to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Popiſh Doctrine of <hi>Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> Penances, and Purgatory; and by reaſon of Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi>'s im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent management of the Conference he had with him, it came to paſs that he rejected the whole Body of Popiſh Doctrine.</q> So that by this we may ſee what was the accidental Occaſion wherein, the ſlender mean, <hi>which in my ſenſe ſmells ſomething of Intereſt,</hi> whereby; and the abject condition of the Perſon by whom, the Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion was ſet on foot. But the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion's a good Reformation, and we have it in the compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive degree. Any Woman will ſay her own <hi>Eggs</hi> are the beſt in the <hi>Market.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now our <hi>Reformling</hi> would be at the <hi>Altar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 49, 50, &amp;c.</note> to level or take it away for our ſuperſtitious Idolatry of <hi>bowing</hi> to it: and he might as well go about to pull the <hi>Sun</hi> out of the Heavens becauſe we bow to the <hi>Eaſt. Ad</hi> and <hi>Verſus,</hi> in his <hi>Grammar,</hi> are all one; but when he proves an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Act of Worſhip of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> performed <hi>towards</hi> the Altar to be Superſtition, I will give his <hi>Worſhip</hi> my Cap, make him a <hi>leg,</hi> and turn to what <hi>point</hi> of the <hi>Compaſſes</hi> his Indifferency pleaſes. Yet our Religion ſhall ſtand unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, no more ſhaken by the breath of Factious Spirits, than the Rays of the Sun are diverted by the <hi>Wind;</hi> blow it from <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What I ſpoke of in the <hi>ſoure</hi> Grape, other <hi>Authors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In the</hi> Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Rack'd.</note> I may ſay, have done in <hi>ſtale</hi> Vinegar, without the Imputation of <hi>abuſive Language,</hi> that ever I heard or read of. <hi>The Royal Charter granted unto Kings,</hi> pag. 125. characterizes the Conception, and Birth, and Education of <hi>John Calvin's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Schiſm with the moſt ſalt and tarteſt Excurſions. <hi>Never was there ſuch a Monſter as this ruling, and thus conſtituted Presbytery; the Father of it Rebellion, the Mother Inſurrection.</hi> Witneſs the Fall of the Prince and Biſhop of <hi>Geneva</hi> to the puny Hiſtorian, our <hi>Obſervator: the Midwife, Sacrilege; the Nurſe, Covetouſneſs, Pride and Ambition; the Milk, Schiſm; the Coats, Armour; the Rattle, Drums; a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174404:16"/>bloody Sword, the Coral; Money,</hi> (and Janus-fac'd too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) <hi>the Babies it delights to play withal: It grows up to be a Stripling, and goes to ſchool to a Council of War; its Leſſon is on a Trumpet; its Feſcue, a Piſtol; its going out of ſchool in rank and file; its Play-days the days of Battel; and Black-Munday the day of Judgment: It comes of age, and is married with a ſolemn League and Covenant; it begets Children like it ſelf, whoſe bleſſing upon them is the power of the ſword, and whoſe impoſition of hands are broken pates; the Monſter cries down this truly ancient Catholick and Apoſtolick Power which the Biſhops exerciſed, and then tacks it up again, and uſe it themſelves in a higher nature than ever any Biſhops or Apoſtles themſelves did or durſt have done, even to the Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Depoſement of their Kings, to the delivering of them up to Satan and to Heads-men, to whom the Apoſtles taught ſubmiſſion (how faulty ſoever they were) and if not obedience, yet ſubmiſſion ſtill to every one of their Ordinances, if not for their own ſakes, yet for the Lord's ſake and for Conſcience-ſake: theſe men cry down the ſame Authority as Popiſh, whilſt they exalt themſelves above all that are called Gods in a higher man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than ever any Pope of Rome ever yet did.</hi> The <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator</hi> might obſerve and remember a certain <hi>Pope</hi> treated an <hi>Emperour</hi> as uncivilly as a <hi>Querry,</hi> in making him hold his Stirrop till he mounted his Horſe,
<note place="margin">Frederick I. <hi>waited on Pope</hi> Adrian<hi>'s Stirrop.</hi>
               </note> walk a foot while he rode: But the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> diſmount our Kings, <hi>hold our Kings in chains, and our Nobles in fetters of Iron,</hi> for <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> to aſcend their <hi>Thrones.</hi> They take from <hi>Caeſar the things which are Caeſars;</hi> not only the <hi>Tribute,</hi> but Crown and Life too. Yet our Government was never long a <hi>Buce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalus,</hi> to be ridden by ſuch new <hi>Maſters</hi> as they: He always knew his <hi>Alexander</hi> from their <hi>uneaſie Sitting,</hi> and they were once fairly thrown out of the <hi>Saddle.</hi> As for their old Arts and new Practices, we know they uſually play at <hi>Tennis</hi> with our <hi>Church;</hi> either ſtrike it <hi>down</hi> like a <hi>Ball</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>rebound</hi> the higher by, or throw it up, as the Beaſt does its prey, only to catch it coming down again in his mouth, devour, and ſport it to ruin; ſo ſome <hi>Paraſites</hi> may be aſſured by experience that the moſt feaſible way to bring a <hi>haughty King down,</hi> is to make him yet a <hi>haughtier Monarch,</hi> pride him, ſtick a <hi>feather</hi> in his Cap to take off his CROWN, and ſo honourably <hi>kick him up ſtairs;</hi> Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174404:16"/>and Drawers are only flung down 'em. The ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſeſt and moſt infallible Maxim, Politick or Religious, that has been ſtated, ſince Philoſophy, Certainty, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration came to perfection, was <hi>King James</hi>'s, in his Baſil. Dor. <hi>Sublato Epiſcopo tollitur Rex.</hi> And the ſame Princely Wiſdom that ſaid <hi>Monarchy and Presbytery</hi> agreed like <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> might have called <hi>Epiſcopacy, Michael</hi> in the Battel. That our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are <hi>Jure divino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 34.</note> I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced from another <hi>Goſpel</hi> than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the Fathers, Councils, <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Epiſcopacy, <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Polity, <hi>Morice</hi>'s Vindication of <hi>Dioceſan Epiſcopacy</hi> againſt <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Church-Hiſtory, and the Learned <hi>Lowth</hi>'s laborious <hi>Subject of Church Power,</hi> &amp;c. He muſt confute them, or he proves nothing. The World's come to this <hi>Gue,</hi> you muſt either trip up another's heels, or he's your <hi>Maſter.</hi> This is the Juggle of <hi>Parity,</hi> they would have no Body <hi>above</hi> them; but we gueſs who they would have <hi>under.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis ſtoried, that after "<hi>Luther</hi> had made a Combuſtion in <hi>Germany</hi> about Religion, he was ſent to by the <hi>Pope,</hi> to be taken off, and offer'd any preferment in the Church, that he would make choice of: <hi>Luther</hi> anſwered, if he had offered half as much at firſt, he would have accepted it; but now he had gone ſo far, he could not come back: in truth he had made himſelf a greater Thing than they could make him; the <hi>German Princes</hi> courted him; he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Author of a Sect ever after to be called <hi>Lutherans.</hi> So have our Preachers done that are againſt the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> they have made themſelves greater with the People, than they can be made the other way, and golden Mountains cannot bring them off now. The <hi>Reformling</hi> is angry that I do not prove every thing out of Scripture, pag. 60. What will become of the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> then, if we cannot find them in the Bible? What ſhall I do for <hi>Words</hi> to fit this <hi>Man,</hi> unleſs I took the length of his Ear, or the meaſure of his Mouth, as the Fellow ſaid that was to make a Speech for my <hi>Lord Mayor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Farther yet the forecited Loyal Author, pag. 136, 137. may as well exemplifie and juſtifie my <hi>Language</hi> as obviate an Objection of an <hi>Elder-date,</hi> which might now be urged. To recite him then: <hi>Oh but the Presbyterians had no hand in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174404:17"/>it, they prayed, and preached, and wrote againſt it, faſted and prayed for a diverſion of all ſuch Intentions: but I pray who took the Scepter out of his hand, in taking away the</hi> Militia, <hi>of which it was an Emblem, that ſhould have defended him; was it not the</hi> Presbyterian? <hi>Who caſt down his Throne by taking away his negative Voice; was it not the</hi> Presbyterian? <hi>Who took off his Crown, the fountain of Honour, from off his Head, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Thoſe Honour on whom he had conferr'd it without them; was it not the</hi> Presbyterian? <hi>Who took away his Supremacy ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify'd by the ſacred Unction wherewith he was anointed, in not allowing him the liberty of his own Conſcience in the point of Epiſcopacy and Church Government; was it not the</hi> Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian? <hi>Who would not treat a minute with their King before they had made him acknowledge himſelf guilty (as they ſay) of all the blood that had been ſpilt throughout his Dominions; was it not the</hi> Presbyterian? <hi>who (notwithſtanding all the Conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on his part that could be granted, even to the very grating his Princely Conſcience when he bid them ask fleſh from off his bones, and he would not deny it them, if it might have been a benefit unto his people, prayed that he might keep his Conſcience whole, it was the Queen-Regent of all good mens Actions, and he hoped there were none would force his Queen before him in his Houſe, as</hi> Ahaſuer us <hi>ſaid to</hi> Haman) <hi>voted not ſatisfactory ſo long, untill the Independant Army came from</hi> Edenburgh, <hi>and ſurpriz'd and murder'd him; was it not the</hi> Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? <hi>He that ſaid the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>held him down by the Hair, while the</hi> Independants <hi>cut off his Head, ſaid true enough; they murder'd him as a King, before ever they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him as a Man; for what may the</hi> Independant <hi>ſay to the</hi> Presbyter? <hi>If you'll take off his Authority, we'll take off his Head: if you'll make him no King, we'll make him no Body: if you'll make him a man of Blood, we'll uſe him accordingly: therefore at your doors,</hi> O Presbyterian <hi>Hypocrites! do I lay his innocent Blood: it is but like the reſt of your Actions commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by your Anceſtors to former Princes all along.</hi> Theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>pan,</hi> and thoſe <hi>gave fire</hi> in the very face of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; as ſome are Deſigners, and others put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, we are miſerably divided in point of Politicks and in point of Religion; and I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Church and State had not occaſion to uſe St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s Litany — <hi>Libera
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174404:17"/>me à me:</hi> and that her true Sons had no need to <q rend="margQuotes">pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Almighty God that he would ſave his Church out of the hands of her Church men, for ſhe now almoſt lies upon the ground like the <hi>Tree</hi> that complained, that ſhe was rent in ſunder by <hi>Wedges</hi> made out of her own Body.</q> But for Diviſions of the <hi>firſt magnitude,</hi> we are beholden to the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> and for a lying <hi>Obſervator</hi> to level my Deſires or Actions at widening the <hi>Gap,</hi> when I wiſh to be a <hi>Phineas</hi> to ſtand in't, and compoſe or repair it with my own ruins, is as irreconcileable a Contradiction, as that I ſhould breath hot and cold at once, or carry the very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Elements of Fire and Water together in my mouth.</p>
            <p>Brotherly Love and Charity are ſacred Commands of the Goſpel, and ſome <hi>Libertines</hi> practiſe them, like the <hi>Oaths in the Play,</hi> as the beſt <hi>broken</hi> Commodities in the Nation: But that we break them in being Zealous for thoſe little Trifles, as <hi>he intimates</hi> our Church-Ceremonies or the Authority of our Church are, I doubt not but 'twould puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle a ſolider Head than an <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s to prove. Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies may be <hi>Trifles,</hi> Play things,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Scotch</hi> Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanan <hi>nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named them ſo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theatrical Fopperies,</hi> by the way of <hi>Obſervatoring,</hi> and he may villifie our Church to a ſanctified ſort of <hi>Gawdy Toyſhop</hi> too, if his <hi>Obſervatorſhip</hi> pleaſe: and from what himſelf meanly advances, I cannot but take a hint of Ridicule on the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> for parting with Chriſtian Union at as ignorant, frivolous, and cheap a rate as a <hi>Fondling</hi> that parts with his whole Eſtate for an Apple in the <hi>Fairing-ſeaſon,</hi> and which a Hobby horſe trap'd with glittering Tinſel from a Pedlars ſhop, or a Rattle, may purchaſe at any time of his unthinking Infancy.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Church</hi> ſtands like the <hi>everywhere</hi> wounded Man in the <hi>Almanack,</hi> pointed and puſh'd at by more Diabolical and Schiſmatical Deſigns, than there are Celeſtial <hi>Signs</hi> in the Heavens: <hi>Aries, Scorpio, Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> are her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all <hi>confederate</hi> to ravage her: The <hi>Planets</hi> have their Goodneſs and Malignancy, and from <hi>Mercury</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with inſulting <hi>Mars</hi> and Oppoſition to us, our <hi>Church</hi> expects no favourable Aſpect or <hi>pacifick Influence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I have done the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> a Diſcourteſie, that's all; and I have done it without breach of <hi>Charity:</hi> and let the <hi>Obſervator</hi> know, though our Opinions differ, it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that our Affections ſhould diſagree. As the beſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174404:18"/>of modern <hi>Epiſtolar Orators</hi> hath obſerved,
<note place="margin">Balſack<hi>'s Letters.</hi>
               </note> The Head and the Heart have their ſeveral Motions and Actions diſtinct: and moral Vertue can reconcile and unite what the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual might <hi>ſeparate.</hi> With Charity I ſay it to them; <hi>Travellers</hi> may fall out by the way, and yet ſet their Horſes up together, and both meet at the ſame Inn at their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney's end. The <hi>Pilgrim</hi> muſt meet with Diſtractions in his Progreſs:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unnyan.</note> I do not mean the <hi>Tinker.</hi> Notwithſtanding there are two principal Things which might advance our Peace and Unanimity ſo far, that we might draw nearer every day, to the great Centre of the <hi>One Religion;</hi> and little elſe would hinder but that we might maintain Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Commerce and <hi>Traffick</hi> in things lawful. FIRST, That the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would leave Preaching up Novelty, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: not maintain our Saviour's Religion by Inſurrection and Rebellion; for this is to maintain it by means condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame <hi>Religion</hi> they would maintain. And SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CONDLY, That they would unlearn their Principle of Fighting for the Liberty and Property of the Subject: The Religious Rebellion's <hi>Stalking-Horſe,</hi> under whoſe Belly the <hi>King</hi> is wounded: ſince thereby the Subjects do alter the very property of their Goods and Eſtates; forfeit, their Great All, their Lives too, which they would ſeem to fight for or preſerve.</p>
            <p>Once more let me tell this <hi>Pſeudo-Moderator,</hi> that much of that <hi>Sarcaſtick</hi> Wit which he miſcalls <hi>abuſive Language,</hi> has been written in Tears and Pity for our Diviſions in point of Religion. As <hi>Howel</hi> neatly complains and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes in <hi>England's Tears,</hi> pag. 10, 11. <q rend="margQuotes">But the principal thing that I hear that Reverend Lady the Church (that Queen of Souls and Key of Heaven) make her moan of, is, that that ſeemleſs Garment of Unity and Love, which our Saviour left her for a Legacy, ſhould be torn and rent into ſo many Sciſſures and Sects by thoſe that would make that Coat which ſhe wore in her infancy, to ſerve her in her riper years: I hear her cry out at the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous exorbitant Liberty that almoſt every capricious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick takes to himſelf to ſhape and form what Religion he liſts: for the World is come now to that paſs, that the Taylor and Shooe-maker may cut out what Religion they pleaſe; the Vintner and Tapſter may baoach what
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174404:18"/>Religion they pleaſe; the Druggiſt and Apothecary may mingle her as they pleaſe; the Haberdaſher may put her upon what Block he pleaſes; the Armourer and Cutler may furbiſh her as they pleaſe; the Dyer may put what Colour, the Painter may put what Face upon her he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; the Weaver may caſt her upon what Loom he pleaſe; the Boat-ſwain and Mariner may bring her to what Dock they pleaſe; the Gardiner may lop her as he pleaſe; the Blackſmith may forge what Religion he pleaſe, and ſo every Artizan, according to his Profeſſion and Fancy, may form her as he pleaſe. Methinks I hear that venerable Matron complain further, how her Pulpits in ſome places are become Beacons; how in lieu of Lights, her Churches up and down are full of Firebands;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 27.</note> how every Caprice of the Brain is termed Tenderneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which well examined, is nothing but ſome fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Fancy, or Frenzy rather of ſome ſhallow-brain'd Scio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt: and whereas others have been uſed to run mad for exceſs of Knowledge, ſome of my Children grow mad now-a-days out of too much ignorance.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Mitre</hi> never wore the <hi>Cleft</hi> with more reaſon of <hi>Diviſion</hi> than for the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Blows it has received; and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'s wonderful that the <hi>Crown</hi> is not cloven too: we are divided in <hi>point of Politicks.</hi> Some Men are like the <hi>mad Fidler,</hi> I remember, that would <hi>run Diviſions</hi> with a clever <hi>Bow</hi> by himſelf; but he could never endure to play in <hi>Conſort:</hi> theſe Humouriſts make bad Muſick and harſh <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> in Church and State. Other <hi>Minions,</hi> when they have got on to the Battlements of our <hi>Church,</hi> are not contented on that Pinnacle, but they muſt <hi>ſtilt</hi> their heights of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over <hi>Civil Policy</hi> too. Theſe are the <hi>Coryphaeus</hi>'s, the <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Gaſſius</hi> that march in the Van of Confuſion: the <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi>'s of Squeak and Diſorder; and it is merciful enough to <hi>thunder</hi> upon ſuch ſingular <hi>Paraſites</hi> and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, whoſe evil Paradoxes it were no Cruelty to anſwer with the <hi>Bolt.</hi> The keeneſt <hi>Satyr</hi> has a charitable <hi>point</hi> enough for ſuch <hi>Eye-ſores</hi> of publick Weal. I would fain ask the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> whether he likes an <hi>Eaſie Majeſty</hi> in this diſſolute chowſing Age, where KINGS are ſlyly gulled and made their <hi>Favourites Cullies?</hi> whom I can compare to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Meteors</hi> appearing glorious for a time, till by their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174404:19"/>yielding more and more to <hi>Court-air-Candidates,</hi> they fall and vaniſh to unnatural Earth. Oh the precarious Grandeur of <hi>Princes,</hi> which is little more than a Tenure of a <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee's Courteſie!</hi> What ſignifies it then for <hi>Kings,</hi> like the Sun in the Firmament of Glory, to look <hi>biggeſt</hi> with gullifying Sciophantry, when they are going down, and muſt never hope to <hi>riſe</hi> again with <hi>Crowns</hi> on their Heads but in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World? If every <hi>Tub</hi> were to ſtand upon its own bottom, I am confident there would be work for the <hi>Cooper:</hi> I ſee nothing ſo abſolute, that does not ſtand in need of <hi>mending,</hi> and nothing mended, but like botch'd <hi>Tinker</hi>'s Work, three <hi>holes</hi> are made for't. The <hi>Obſervator</hi> and I agree in one Opinion, that the Reconciliation of the <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amites</hi> and <hi>Jacobites</hi> is very <hi>improbable:</hi> and I fancy it is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible</hi> too for our WEEKLY SOLOMON to moderate their Contentions ſucceſsfully with all his Statiſm, and give the <hi>Child to the right Owner.</hi> The Sword muſt decide that Quarrel. Yet I am apt to believe that his <hi>boaſted Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity</hi> would not, like the <hi>unnatural WOMAN,</hi> have it <hi>divided:</hi> though the <hi>indifferent Man's moderation</hi> perhaps might be willing to <hi>go halves</hi> or part <hi>ſtakes</hi> with the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, play what <hi>Game</hi> of Religion you pleaſe. Will he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this <hi>Motto</hi> for himſelf — <hi>Regis ad Exemplum componi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Obſervator?</hi> Cannot he <hi>trim</hi> as thoſe at the <hi>Helm ſteer?</hi> He may bluſter and mediate with a <hi>Pennyworth</hi> of <hi>Weekly Scribble</hi> for a PEACE, and Heaven could not ſend a <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comer preſent</hi> on Earth: but to call him a STATESMAN for this, were <q rend="margQuotes">to Knight a Mandrake, to view him through a magnifying <hi>Perſpective,</hi> and by that groſs Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole to give the Reputation of an <hi>Engineer</hi> to a Maker of <hi>Mouſe-traps.</hi>
               </q> He may ſee all his Beauties and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a true Reflection of Queen <hi>Mab</hi>'s Regiſter's Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs; and read his own in CLIEVELAND's Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Diurnal-Maker. A <hi>Stateſman!</hi> by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that <hi>Sir Roger L'eſtrange</hi> is no Stateſman, no <hi>Obſervator</hi> ſuperlative, none of the beſt <hi>Tranſlator</hi>'s of the letter'd World. A Stateſman! yes, as much as <hi>Merry Andrew</hi> laſt <hi>Bartholomew-Fair</hi> but one, would needs pretend to be an <hi>Admiral,</hi> and put to Sea with a Ship called the TOWER, take the <hi>Monument</hi> for the <hi>Main-maſt,</hi> and make ſuch a DESCENT, that <hi>Neptune</hi> ſhould tremble and drop his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174404:19"/>Trident, and the <hi>Tyrant of France flag him.</hi> Have a care of a <hi>Mercurius Britannicus Vapulans:</hi> the <hi>Punchanello</hi> was ſoundly <hi>whip'd</hi> for his Jeſt. A Stateſman! a Plagiary rather, that ſtruts in borrowed Plumes, and makes a great Figure and Shew of the <hi>Frippery</hi> and <hi>Brocage</hi> of Gazettes and <hi>Foreign Prints: Mercury</hi> was always Thie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and <hi>Filching.</hi> Let him be put in the <hi>Gazette</hi> for the amuſing Intelligencer, and the deluded Country's Bubble: the Hawkers and Coffee-Houſe <hi>Wholeſail Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant</hi> for Politicks: and that may make him talk ſo much of my <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> in the <hi>Lump,</hi> for he can no more ſpeak it, I ſuppoſe, than ſome ſell, by <hi>Retail.</hi> This <hi>general Nonſenſe</hi> muſt be much of the ſame Line and Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>accumulative Treaſon: Twins</hi> of the ſame <hi>Nonſenſical</hi> Brain perhaps. <hi>Accumulative Treaſon</hi> is a huddle of <hi>Nonſenſe;</hi> Nonſenſe is Nonſenſe, as a Block's a Block all the World over: and ſo both have the ſame <hi>complex face</hi> and feature, wrought up like a Maſs of <hi>Paſte</hi> or Puff before it has received its <hi>Chriſtmas-form,</hi> or dough-bak'd a <hi>Pye</hi> with half an <hi>Obſervator</hi> under it. <hi>Accumulative Treaſon,</hi> I hope, is to be no <hi>Precedent</hi> for taking a <hi>man's life away:</hi> He may remember, THAT for THIS was no <hi>Nonſenſe,</hi> for it had a <hi>capital meaning</hi> in it; and a notable Conſtruction could behead a <hi>Peer</hi> for a <hi>Monoſyllable. Nonſenſe</hi> indeed, it may be, is as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with an <hi>Author</hi>'s credit, as a <hi>Nobleman</hi>'s Head was thought with his <hi>Shoulders,</hi> without any fairer Law or farther Examination. Yea, but he particularizes: <hi>In my ſecond Page I look upon Calviniſm as an Hereſie as dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable as Socinianiſm, Arrianiſm, and Anabaptiſm,</hi> and ſo our <hi>Reformling</hi> has it pag. 65. and this is <hi>peccant Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe</hi> with a vengeance. Can the <hi>Reader</hi> believe the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <hi>Obſervator</hi> ever read this <hi>Pamphlet</hi> by his miſquotation of the <hi>ſecond page</hi> for the <hi>eleventh?</hi> But a falſe Report, a falſe ſtep in the <hi>Threſhold,</hi> is an eaſie Miſtake in a <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay and Say-ſo Writer;</hi> and I eſteem him little elſe than a <hi>Hackney</hi> or Huckſter of other Mens Notions: Political Inventions are cheap indeed that are cry'd off at <hi>Two Bunches a penny Ho.</hi> I appeal to any Man of <hi>Letters,</hi> or ſo much <hi>Logick</hi> as he has been born with; Whether
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174404:20"/>there be <hi>Nonſenſe,</hi> or even Abſurdity, in theſe <hi>Words: If an Enemy is ſuffered to come in upon us, he may eaſily wreſtle us into his mercy, and the melancholly Stander-by may ſee us thrown at their will and pleaſure into Socinianiſm, Arrianiſm, Anabaptiſm, Calviniſm, Commonwealthiſm, or any other Heretical-iſm, to the utter abolition of our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or downfall, ruin, and rubbiſh of the Fundamentals as well as Ceremonies of our Religion and Devotion.</hi> Reformer Rack'd,
<note place="margin">J. G. G's <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication.</hi>
               </note> pag. 11. Now let <hi>Them</hi> both open their Eyes, and ſee their own blind Miſconſtruction: <hi>Any other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical-iſm,</hi> has no manner of relation to any of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going <hi>Terms,</hi> much leſs particularly to CALVINISM: the Expreſſion is aptly and clearly diſtinguiſhed from them, inaſmuch as <hi>other-iſms</hi> points at <hi>Neſtorianiſm, Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianiſm,</hi> or ſuch like <hi>other</hi> Heretical iſms; if the <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> pleaſes, <hi>Arminianiſm:</hi> and they do not know but I meant peculiarly the late <hi>Maſoniſm.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The late</hi> Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenarian <hi>in Bucking ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
               </note> Moreover, if it had a connexed relation to any of the forementioned HERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIES or <hi>Words;</hi> how comes it to be <hi>Nonſenſe?</hi> For if in any juſt <hi>Senſe,</hi> CALVINISM may be called Heretical, I hope it is not <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> to call it ſo: now that <hi>Hereſie</hi> hath a large and a ſtricter <hi>Senſe</hi> is plain; <hi>it</hi> may ſignifie an Erroneous <hi>Sect,</hi> according to the <hi>Etymon</hi> of <hi>Election</hi> or <hi>Diviſion,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whether Theme they pleaſe: ſo the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> alſo laudably uſed it to ſignifie a <hi>Dogma</hi> or an Opinion, good or ill: ſtrictly taken, <hi>it</hi> ſignifies in the <hi>Schools,</hi> an Opinion contrary to ſound and fundamental Principles of Religion. Hence the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi>'s Axioms, <hi>Non quilibet Error facit Haereticum: Non omnis Schiſmaticus eſt Hareticus.</hi> Wolleb. Th. Chriſt. pag. 137. <hi>Schiſmaticus eſt qui ſalvo fidei fundamento à ritu ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo Eccleſiae petulanter &amp; ambitionis ſtudio diſcedit:</hi> But he goes on; <hi>aut enim erratur</hi> (meaning <hi>ab Haeretico) in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damento; ut fit ab Arrianis &amp; Marcionitis, quorum illi Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, hi vero humanitatem Chriſti negant: aut circa fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum; qualiter Errant Pontificii docentes tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiationem, quâ naturae humanae Chriſti veritas tollitur: aut praeter fundamentum, quales Errores à Paulo faeno, ligno,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>aſſimilantur,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. And, in fine, that CALVINISM is <hi>Heretical</hi> in a larger Acceptation, and in the ſtricter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174404:20"/>ſenſe of Hereſie, PRAETER FUNDAMENTUM, I aſſert. Through the <hi>Labyrinths of Logick</hi> is not the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt way to Heaven, nor overmuch Curioſity the readieſt courſe to ſearch out Truth by: Nevertheleſs, if they will have Recourſe to their <hi>Ante-Predicaments,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that it is only,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtotle's Organon.</note> 
               <hi>Analogum per ſe poſitum quod praeſumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſtare pro famoſiore analogato;</hi> and but make out Their Calumny of <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> upon my Aſſertion, by proving, <hi>à Conſilio,</hi> that there cannot be aſſigned any reaſon of an analogical Dependance or <hi>Similitude</hi> between CALVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISM and ARRIANISM, &amp;c. <hi>Cur conveniant in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Haereſeos,</hi> I will recant my Error as willingly as he that makes as common a <hi>Trade of Begging Pardons</hi> as of <hi>Writing pieces of Scandal.</hi> What Impertinence is it for <hi>Them</hi> to ſay, I look upon CALVINISM as an Hereſie as damnable as Socinianiſm, Arrianiſm, and Anabaptiſm; when the Diſtinction and <hi>Degrees</hi> of their Wickedneſs is manifeſted in the <hi>Cadence</hi> of the Sentence: where I allot the Deſtruction of the Fundamentals of our <hi>Religion</hi> to Arrianiſm, Socinianiſm, or Anabaptiſm; and the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition or Abrogation of our Lawful <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> only to Calviniſm or Commonwealthiſm? So the <hi>Phyſician</hi> may preſcribe to his <hi>Patient</hi> againſt Peaſe-Pottage, Livers, Lights, Haſty-Pudding, Wine, Cherries; they are bad for <hi>him</hi> in a Fever, and unwholſome Food in a ſane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brisk Conſtitution: yet he would not have all theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik'd with an equal <hi>Diſguſt.</hi> But to give <hi>Mr. Obſervator</hi> a more ſenſible Example of his Miſunderſtanding: if I mention ATWOOD, <hi>Bellwood, Wellwood, Elwood,</hi> or any other <hi>ill Wood;</hi> yet perhaps I ſhould never find ſuch a <hi>ſpecial Stick</hi> as he, nor mean to bring the <hi>reſt</hi> into equal Diſgrace of Prodigality and <hi>Profuſeneſs</hi> of Pen, Tongue, or <hi>Eſtate</hi> with <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their great Concern for <hi>Unity</hi> in Religion, they may imagine will juſtifie them in branding me with <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> and <hi>abuſive Language:</hi> This is pretty Sophiſtry with a witneſs; as <hi>Quiblers,</hi> when ſtrain'd, and have little more to ſay, make uſe of a true Propoſition to infer and <hi>quirk</hi> in an Erroneous Concluſion: Fallacies are difficultly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, but eaſily refuted and ſolved after a Diſcovery.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174404:21"/>
               <hi>Pettifoggers</hi> will ſtill be citing Law as quick and <hi>voluble</hi> as <hi>Mercury,</hi> to authorize their Injuſtice, <hi>Barretry,</hi> and Vexations. The <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Religion, I ſurmiſe, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed according to the fundamental <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Scold,</hi> of Railery. How ſhould we expect an <hi>Harmonicon</hi> in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords; a Peace or Reconciliation with thoſe Zealots who are ſo <hi>madded</hi> with Spirit, and I know not what of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotry of Perſuaſion, that they are fitter to pick <hi>Straws</hi> in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> than to Preach or Lecture an <hi>Union</hi> about the Nation? One is for <hi>ſhoving the heavy ars'd Chriſtian to Heaven,</hi> or making <hi>high-heel'd ſhooes for the Dwarf in Chriſt.</hi> Another wildly harangues, that if we have not better Succeſs with our Arms againſt <hi>Turkiſh Lewis,</hi> the enſuing Campaign, he will conclude that <hi>God is turn'd Jacobite:</hi>
               <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verley. Burgeſs.</note> But he prayed that he would rather ſtand <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and have no more to do in our <hi>Camps</hi> than the <hi>Kings of Sweden and Denmark.</hi> A third found <hi>King William</hi> out in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> but not till ſome time after the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> landed at <hi>Torbay:</hi> while the poor <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationer</hi> miſtook the <hi>Fleet-priſon</hi> for God's Cabinet. This is their <hi>Triumvirate</hi> of Frenzy; and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> Gullery.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reformling,</hi> pag. 36.69. repeats — <hi>Were it better to wrap up our Goſpel-Talents in an idle Napkin of Silence and Oblivion, than to preach and Evangelize the Jews out of the pale of the Chriſtian Church?</hi> Reform. Rack'd, p. 19. for a piece of uncharitable Monſtroſity. Was the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> crucified, the Lord of Eternal Life put to Death? And do not the <hi>Jews</hi> disbelieve the whole Hiſtory? Muſt they not be told they are no Chriſtians then? That they are of the wrong ſide of the Hedge or <hi>Pale?</hi> Yet if the <hi>Unbelievers</hi> will come <hi>over,</hi> we are willing to <hi>lend them a hand,</hi> and think it no <hi>Treſpaſs.</hi> That they would come <hi>in</hi> and <hi>welcome,</hi> is the meaning of my <hi>Evangelizing</hi> them <hi>out.</hi> But he handles the <hi>Napkin</hi> as if he had got the <hi>Glander</hi> with a <hi>Horſe-pox</hi> to him, and makes no better uſe of it, than the <hi>Widow in Don Quevedo,</hi> throwing <hi>Snot</hi> about the Mourning-Room. He might as well have buſied himſelf about computing how many <hi>Buſhels of Flegm</hi> would go to manuring an <hi>Acre of Land,</hi> as in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174404:21"/>
               <hi>ſniveling</hi> at me and miſrepreſenting an <hi>idle Napkin of Oblivion and Silence:</hi> might as well have ſaid <hi>they</hi> had waſhed their hands cleaner than <hi>Pilot</hi> in a <hi>Laver</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and that the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mooriſh Infidels,</hi> whoſe Religion lies not in their <hi>Skins</hi> I confeſs, were now as <hi>fair Chriſtians</hi> as any in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To call Mr. <hi>Obſervator</hi> a Bankrupt of Reaſon as well as Eſtate, would be but <hi>Fleet-Language;</hi> and he may keep his Tongue a priſoner to his Heart <hi>there</hi> too, his Pen to his Ink-Bottle, his politick Thoughts to his Head; for he's indebted more to the <hi>News-monger</hi> for acceptance and peruſal of <hi>Mercurius Britannicus,</hi> than ever he will be able to repay with Wit or <hi>Policy.</hi> But if <hi>Obſervator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is his Livelihood, I ſhall give him free leave to have a fling at me when he pleaſes; no, to make me his <hi>Jack-a-lent,</hi> as many <hi>Throws</hi> as he will, if he can make a <hi>penny on't.</hi> And if I ſuffer a <hi>Shrove-Tueſdays perſecution</hi> to get him a Meſs of <hi>Cock-broth;</hi> will not he <hi>dye</hi> me with <hi>Red</hi> for a Martyr of my own Folly, in his Diary?</p>
            <p>How Authoritatively he <hi>Lords</hi> it over the <hi>High-Churchmen</hi> with Bluſter, Rancour, and Bile! He can find nothing but <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> among them, can hear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the <hi>Pulpit on the Day of King</hi> Charles<hi>'s Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, but Invectives, railing Accuſations, and abuſive Language, inſtead of Chriſtian Exhortations to Repentance, Union, and Charity:</hi> and his appealing to all the <hi>Sermons</hi> that have been publiſhed on that Subject, is notorious; juſt ſuch another <hi>Appeal</hi> to prove HIMSELF mendacious, as SOME BODY brought to prove Himſelf a <hi>Cuckold.</hi> He <hi>romances</hi> yet a little farther, and calls me a <hi>Champion</hi> of our Church: Chriſtendom had but ſeven: I thank him for the honour of an <hi>Eighth Champion,</hi> and return him a SAPIENTUM OCTAVUS for that.</p>
            <p>How Magiſterial he is with his pennyworth of <hi>Licenſed Scribble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 19.</note> and the <hi>Reformling</hi> Pedant with his Laſh of Puniſhment, in dealing with me not by Argument but <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> not by their vaunted Moderation, but Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of having <hi>me</hi> made an Example, and our Church purged of me too? And had they the power of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the arbitrary By-Laws of their <hi>Sic volo</hi>'s, Croſs and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:174404:22"/>Pile whether they would make any <hi>Bones</hi> of Difference, whether I, or the Cauſe I ſatyrically wrote for and ſtill eſpouſe with the ſame unblunted edge, ſhould drop and periſh. But the <hi>Obſervator's Mercury</hi> has not cured my <hi>itch</hi> of Writing: it tickles the more; and I ſhall never ſollicit them to a Ceſſation of the innocent Arms of Pen, Ink, and Paper, let Them <hi>rally</hi> again as ſoon as they can <hi>accoutre.</hi> They cannot diſturb my Reputation and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dateneſs, ſo long as they cannot plunder or <hi>ſequeſtre me</hi> of this Humour —<hi>Alte non temo &amp; humili non Sdegno.</hi> The <hi>Cynick</hi> vied Conqueſts with the <hi>Great: I neither fear the High, nor diſdain the Low.</hi> For I eſteem it no Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to be cenſured by thoſe whom I would account it no Credit or Applauſe to be favoured by: Should an <hi>Obſervator</hi> commend my <hi>Travels,</hi> I ſhould call my ſelf in queſtion, and task my Thoughts with a ſtricter Scrutiny, whether I had not ſat all my Life in the <hi>Chimney-Corner,</hi> and never got farther out of the <hi>Smoak,</hi> than the <hi>home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Girl</hi> that was got on to the top of a high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and cry'd, Whoo Father, <hi>Here's another World.</hi> A Man ſhould never <hi>publiſh</hi> any thing, but only read his own <hi>Compoſures</hi> to his own Ears and make <hi>Wall-Lectures</hi> of them, if he were afraid of <hi>awaking Envy.</hi> When the time of <hi>Paper-Kiteing</hi> comes about, and highflown <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators</hi> make up moſt of the giddy Airy thing; I ſhall not <hi>truckle</hi> under any other <hi>Wing</hi> but Truth's, let him take me up like a <hi>Chicken</hi> or <hi>Gizzard,</hi> prey upon me <hi>Hagard-like,</hi> and <hi>whiſtle</hi> the Inſolence of his falſe Triumph to the Publick. Nevertheleſs, one Courteſie I muſt beg of my Adverſaries, when the <hi>Clumſy Mercury</hi> and the <hi>Reformling</hi> decypher my Intentions; not to tell a <hi>Tale of a Tub,</hi> not to make me intend what they pleaſe, not to adapt ſuch foreign Idea's to my Words and Phraſe, not to put ſuch a vaſt difference between my <hi>Text</hi> and their <hi>Commentaries,</hi> and laſtly, not ſtupidly or maliciouſly to wreſt my Senſe, and put me to the trouble of being my <hi>own Interpreter</hi> again; for I have only given <hi>Them</hi> a fair MARFORIO for their PASQUIN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174404:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
